<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-18T09:11:10+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers.xml</id><title type="html">The Republic of Agora | Hkers</title><subtitle>UNITE THE PUBLIC ♢ VOL.15 © MMXXII</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Invasion Update 2/24</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-24-ukraine-conflict-update-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Invasion Update 2/24" /><published>2022-02-24T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-24T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-24-ukraine-conflict-update-7.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 23-24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ukrainian forces are successfully slowing Russian offensives on all axes of advance other than a Russian breakout from the Crimean Peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian failure to ground the Ukrainian air force or cripple Ukrainian command and control is likely enabling these initial Ukrainian successes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian forces remain much larger and more capable than Ukraine’s conventional military and Putin is likely to defeat Ukrainian regular military forces and secure his territorial objectives in the coming days or weeks if he is willing to pay the price.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ukrainian forces defeated a Russian operation to isolate Kyiv from the west, recapturing the Hostomel military airport from Russian VDV (Airborne) troops after several counterattacks throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian forces are rapidly advancing north from Crimea, securing Kherson city. Their deepest penetration to date is about 60 kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian forces are advancing on Kyiv from Belarus on both sides of the Dnipro River, but have been temporarily halted east of the Dnipro at Chernihiv.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian forces likely seek to cut off Ukrainian troops on the line of contact in Donbas using an envelopment behind the Ukrainian front lines through Luhansk Oblast. Russian frontal assaults have taken little territory in Donetsk and Luhansk at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin seeks to obfuscate to Russian citizens that he launched a large-scale invasion of Ukraine aimed at regime change, likely to mitigate blowback from a Russian population unprepared for a major war.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The United States and its European allies approved sweeping new sanctions against Russia’s economic, military, technological, and energy sectors but attempted to mitigate the possible consequences of those sanctions for US and EU energy markets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US and NATO allies deployed additional forces to NATO’s eastern flank to deter a spillover from Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;International organizations warned of a looming humanitarian crisis as states bordering Ukraine deployed troops to their borders to prepare for a possible influx of Ukrainian refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kremlin detained hundreds of civilians across Russia for protesting the Russian invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.criticalthreats.org/wp-content/uploads/UkraineCoTFeb242022-645x1024.png&quot; alt=&quot;ISW Assessed Control of Terrain in Ukraine and Main Russian Maneuver Axes, 2022.2.24&quot; /&gt;
▲ Assessed Control of Terrain in Ukraine and Main Russian Maneuver Axes, 2022.2.24, by ISW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin began a large-scale invasion of Ukraine on February 24 likely aimed at full regime change and the occupation of Ukraine. Russian forces met several setbacks on the first day of major offensive operations. However, Russian forces remain much larger and more capable than Ukraine’s conventional military. Russia will likely defeat Ukrainian regular military forces and secure their territorial objectives at some point in the coming days or weeks if Putin is determined to do so and willing to pay the cost in blood and treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian military operations began with a short and incomplete air campaign on February 24 around 4:00 am local time targeting Ukrainian air defenses, supply depots, and airfields across unoccupied Ukraine. US defense officials estimate initial strikes comprised over 100 missiles including a mix of short and medium-range ballistic missiles, cruise missiles, and sea-launched missiles. Russia did not successfully ground the Ukrainian air force or cripple the Ukrainian armed forces, enabling several Ukrainian successes on February 24. Russia has not demonstrated its full air and missile capabilities and will likely conduct further waves of strikes in the coming days aimed at degrading Ukraine’s command and control and ability to redeploy forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian forces recaptured the Hostomel military airport, 20 km northwest of Kyiv, from Russian VDV (airborne) troops likely from the 31st Guards Air Assault Brigade as of 11:00 pm local time after several unsuccessful counterattacks earlier in the day. Russian airborne forces were additionally unable to secure the Boryspil airport (Kyiv’s primary international airport), southeast of Kyiv. Ukraine’s contestation of the airport prevents Russia from airlifting reinforcements to isolate Kyiv from western Ukraine, as feared earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian ground forces are advancing on four primary axes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Belarus/Kyiv axis: Russian forces in Belarus are advancing on Kyiv along both sides of the Dnipro River, likely seeking to isolate Kyiv. Russian forces have made greater progress west of the Dnipro, successfully securing the Chernobyl exclusion zone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kharkiv axis: Russian forces, including confirmed elements of the 1st Guards Tank Army, are conducting a frontal assault on Kharkiv from northeastern Ukraine. Ukrainian forces are temporarily halting Russian advances but Russian forces will likely enter Kharkiv before the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donbas axis: Russian forces, likely elements of the 8th Combined Arms Army, are conducting an envelopment through Luhansk Oblast rather than a frontal assault from the Russian-occupied Donbas. Russian forces likely seek to cut off Ukrainian forces on the line of contact and/or drive them out of their prepared defensive positions, forcing them to fight in the open.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crimea axis: Russian forces are making their greatest territorial gains advancing north from Crimea. Russian forces have reportedly penetrated to a depth of at least 60 km and captured Kherson city, securing access to the Crimean Canal. President Zelensky identified the attack from Crimea as the “most problematic situation.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin seeks to obfuscate to Russian citizens that he launched a large-scale invasion of Ukraine on February 24 aimed at regime change likely to mitigate blowback from a Russian population unprepared for a major war. Putin’s claimed objectives to “de-nazify” and “demilitarize” Ukraine are a transparent cover for an unprovoked war of aggression to occupy a neighboring state. Putin and other Kremlin officials repeatedly claimed Russia’s offensive is a “limited operation” necessary to defend against false Russian claims of an imminent Ukrainian offensive against Donbas and refused to call it a war. Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitry Peskov refused to expand on the specific objectives of the Russian military operation in Ukraine, stating the Kremlin is interested in direct negotiations with Ukraine to secure Kyiv’s official neutrality between the West and Russia and the removal of all “weapons.” Ukraine’s government is unlikely to agree to Putin’s demands. The Kremlin likely seeks to portray its offensive war as a limited action to the Russian population to prevent blowback after months of repeated denials Russia would launch an offensive against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin is presenting tightly controlled and largely fictitious media coverage of Russian operations in Ukraine to support the false narratives that Russia is not engaged in a large-scale invasion of Ukraine and that Russian forces are easily succeeding. Russia’s Ministry of Defense is not publishing updates beyond cherrypicked video briefings in contrast with the Ukrainian government’s constant updates on both successes and failures. Kremlin-sponsored TV programs do not show videos of explosions, battles, and military movements throughout Ukraine, presenting the conflict as occurring mainly in the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR). Kremlin newswire TASS has not provided significant information on damaged infrastructure throughout Ukraine. Russian TV outlets emphasize that the Russian Armed Forces only targeted 74 airstrikes at Ukrainian military infrastructure and supposedly disabled 11 airfields, 18 air defense radar stations, and a Ukrainian naval base while downplaying Russian ground troop presence in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian media claims that the Ukrainian military is collapsing are likely aimed to reassure Russians that the war will end quickly and victoriously but could also reflect the Russian government’s erroneous expectations. Russian TV is amplifying claims that Russian operations will be quick and successful, falsely asserting that Ukrainian troops are surrendering en masse. Russian defense media cites fabricated social media reports that frustrated nationalists have opened fire against surrendering Ukrainian units. Russian media highlights claimed Russian humanitarian efforts in the context of fabricated Ukrainian mass surrenders, amplifying Russian Defense Minister Sergey Shoigu’s special instructions for Russian troops to create safe corridors for surrendering Ukrainian servicemen on February 24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of Russian civilians protested Russia’s invasion of Ukraine in several major cities despite state crackdowns and mass arrests on February 24. Protesters in Moscow, St Petersburg, Yekaterinburg, and 54 other cities chanted “no to war” and waved Ukrainian flags amid a heavy presence by Russian riot police. Russian celebrities, political activists, sports stars, and artists condemned the war in statements on social media and to Western media outlets. Russia’s Investigative Committee threatened to track down protest organizers and demonstrators, promising “severe punishment for mass riots.” Russian police detained at least 966 demonstrators in Moscow and 432 in St Petersburg according to civil rights group OVD-Info. Russian President Vladimir Putin likely intended to use a series of planned false flag attacks to build a media narrative and support for his invasion of Ukraine among the Russian public. However, repeated US and Ukrainian exposure of planned Russian actions likely led Putin to begin the invasion without widespread public backing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;belarusian-activity&quot;&gt;Belarusian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko gave a speech on February 24 setting information conditions for possible Belarusian operations against NATO’s eastern flank, claiming Belarusian troops will defend against a NATO “stab in the back” and falsely claiming Poland may attack Belarus. ISW has not observed any Belarusian forces operating in Ukraine as of February 24, though Lukashenko stated they will join Russian operations in Ukraine “if necessary.” Lukashenko stated Belarusian forces are shifting their efforts to protect Belarus’s border with Poland and Lithuania to prevent NATO from “stabbing Russia in the back.” Lukashenko further claimed the Polish government “needs a war” to obfuscate its domestic unpopularity. Belarusian Defense Minister’s Aide for Ideology Major-General Leonid Kasinsky stated that Belarusian troops are reinforcing its borders to prevent an enemy “surprise attack” rather than participate in Russian operations in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States, the European Union (EU), and the United Kingdom announced new sanctions packages against Russia’s economic, military, technological, and energy sectors on February 24. US President Joe Biden announced sanctions on major Russian banks and their subsidiaries; debt and equity restrictions on critical Russian enterprises and entities; additional sanctions on Russian elites and their family members; and restrictions on US exports to Russia. Biden also announced sanctions on 24 Belarusian individuals, two Belarusian state-owned banks, nine defense firms, and seven Belarusian regime-connected officials and elites for supporting Russia’s invasion of Ukraine. Biden added that direct sanctions on Russian President Vladimir Putin are “still on the table.” EU leaders held a February 24 emergency summit in Brussels to approve a second round of joint sanctions against Russia. EU-adjacent countries including Switzerland, Israel, and Turkey condemned Russia’s invasion of Ukraine but stopped short of joining European sanctions as of February 24. The United Kingdom also announced comprehensive sanctions covering Russian elites, companies, and financial institutions, completely shutting off Russia’s banking system from UK financial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sanctions packages did not cut Russia off from the SWIFT high-security payment network, which could have imposed high costs on Russia’s financial activity abroad but would also likely spark an energy crisis in European countries that rely on Russian imports. The foreign ministers of Ukraine, Latvia, Estonia, and Lithuania called on the EU to end Russia’s participation in SWIFT but Biden said on February 24 that removing Russia from SWIFT is not “the direction the rest of Europe wants go at this moment.” Biden emphasized that the sanctions the United States imposed on Russian banks are “of equal consequence, maybe more consequence” than removing Russia from SWIFT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-and-eu-activity&quot;&gt;NATO and EU Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US and NATO allies deployed additional forces to NATO’s eastern flank to deter and prevent spillover from Russia’s invasion of Ukraine on February 24. NATO Secretary-General Jens Stoltenberg stated on February 24 that NATO has activated defense plans to enable force deployments “where necessary,” including the capability to activate the NATO Response Force. NATO will deploy “additional land and sea forces to the eastern part of the Alliance” and will place air support on standby to strengthen the security and defense of its allies. The United States deployed 7,000 US troops already stationed in Europe to Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, and Romania; authorized additional US forces to be sent from the United States to Germany; extended the stay of 500 US troops in Lithuania; and authorized an unspecified number of F-35 fighter jets to Estonia. The US Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) declared an expansion of its existing flight ban on US civilian aircraft over parts of Eastern Europe and Russian airspace to include all of Ukraine, Belarus, and western Russia. Germany sent 350 additional combat troops to Lithuania and three additional fighter jets to Romania.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern European states including Moldova, Slovakia, Hungary, and Poland deployed troops to their borders to brace for a possible mass arrival of Ukrainian refugees. The Lithuanian and Moldovan governments declared states of emergency on February 24. Lithuania deployed an unspecified number of forces along its borders with Belarus on February 24. Denmark announced on February 24 that it will deploy 200 troops to Estonia and two F-16 fighter jets to police Poland’s air space in early March while preparing an additional battalion of 700-800 soldiers to contribute to NATO’s defense operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO member states Poland, Estonia, Latvia, Slovakia, and Lithuania triggered Article 4 to launch consultations within NATO as a protective measure on February 24, triggering additional NATO deployments to its eastern flank. Article 4 of the Washington Treaty allows member states to start formal consultations if a member state feels threatened, and can lead to collective NATO action. NATO Secretary-General Jens Stoltenberg underscored that NATO will continue taking all necessary measures to bolster security by deploying additional land, air, and sea forces against Russia’s threat to Euro-Atlantic security. Stoltenberg called on Russia to withdraw its military forces from Ukraine and engage in dialogue with NATO. Stoltenberg called for a virtual summit of NATO heads of state on February 25 to discuss NATO’s response. Separately, US Secretary of State Antony Blinken and US Secretary of Defense Lloyd Austin emphasized that the US commitment to NATO Article 5 mutual defense commitment is “ironclad” in a call with NATO Secretary General Stoltenberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern European states and international aid organizations are preparing for a major influx of Ukrainian refugees. United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres announced the UN will release $20 million from its humanitarian relief fund to support Ukrainian civilians. The UN High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) also stated its readiness to supply aid to Ukrainian civilians and urged neighboring countries to keep their borders open to accept Ukrainian refugees. The UNHCR estimates that several thousand Ukrainian refugees have fled to northern Moldova and Romania and approximately 10,000 have been displaced within Ukraine since Russia’s invasion began on February 24. The World Health Organization warned of a possible “humanitarian catastrophe” and expressed concern for civilians caught in the conflict. The Polish government announced it expects as many as one million Ukrainian refugees to enter Poland. Members of the US 82nd Airborne Infantry Brigade and Combat Team began preparations to assist local authorities in hosting refugees in Rzeszow, Poland. Germany announced it would provide aid to Poland and other neighbors in the event of a large-scale refugee crisis. Hungary and Slovakia also deployed troops along their borders with Ukraine to manage the expected influx of refugees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China refused to condemn the Russian invasion of Ukraine and announced new imports from Russia that could mitigate the impacts of Western sanctions on February 24. Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Hua Chunying denied China supported Russia’s invasion of Ukraine but refused to condemn it during a February 24 press conference. Hua Chunying stressed the importance of joint cooperation and addressing the legitimate security concerns of all parties. Hua Chunying accused the United States of “fueling [the] fire” of tensions. Hua Chunying also announced an agreement for China to import additional Russian wheat — a possible lifeline for the Russian economy and an early indicator of China’s future approach to Western sanctions against Russia. Hua Chunying claimed that China and Russia finalized the agreement during Russian President Vladimir Putin’s February 4 visit to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 23-24.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/uTJ9KsM.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/uTJ9KsM.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/23</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-23-ukraine-conflict-update-6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/23" /><published>2022-02-23T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-23T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-23-ukraine-conflict-update-6.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 22-23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proxy leaders of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) formally asked Putin to deploy Russian forces into DNR and LNR territory on February 23. The DNR and LNR leadership also requested Russian assistance to gain control over the rest of Donetsk and Luhansk Oblasts, which they illegally claim as rightfully theirs. Putin secured unlimited parliamentary approval to deploy Russian forces abroad for any purpose he chooses on February 22. A Russian deployment to the DNR and LNR would set conditions for successive or simultaneous Russian military operations to conquer the entire Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts and large areas of Ukrainian territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Russian state TV set information conditions to justify a full-scale invasion and occupation of Ukraine to the Russian people. State media denied Ukrainian sovereignty and circulated repeated fabricated claims of Ukrainian aggression. Russia may conduct additional spectacular false flag attacks to legitimize their invasion to the Russian public. However, the repeated US and Ukrainian exposure of Russia’s planned false flag attacks in recent days may lead Putin to begin his invasion without the public justification he desired. The current Russian state TV information operations, along with Putin’s speeches, suggest that Putin may intend to annex all or most of Ukraine directly to Russia after conquering it rather than setting up some sort of puppet state in Kyiv. Evidence for Putin’s post-invasion intentions remains inconclusive at this time, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Russian proxy Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics formally asked Russian President Vladimir Putin to deploy Russian Armed Forces to Donbas, setting conditions for an immediate deployment of Russian ground forces at scale into Donbas and toward the line of contact.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Satellite imagery and Western intelligence indicate an imminent full-scale invasion with additional Russian deployments to Belgorod near Kharkiv, northeastern Ukraine, and in Gomel, Belarus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian state TV implied that Ukraine does not have rights to sovereignty over most of its territory, setting information conditions for the Russian population to support a Russian invasion and occupation of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The United States forward-deployed additional forces to Europe to support NATO allies and deter Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US and allied leaders canceled planned meetings with Russian officials due to Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European Union (EU) and the United States are likely leveraging Russia’s unprecedented aggression against Ukraine as a catalyst to transition the EU away from its current dependence on Russian natural gas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia continued deploying ground forces and rotary-wing aircraft to likely assembly areas near the Ukrainian border in Gomel, Belarus, and Belgorod, Russia, on February 22. Satellite imagery observed a new Russian military field camp with over 100 vehicles in Gomel, Belarus, on February 22. Belarusian social media users reported T-72 tank elements, likely of the Russian 64th Motorized Rifle Brigade, in Mazur, Gomel, Belarus, on February 22. Russia deployed at least 30 Russian Ka-52 attack helicopters and Mi-8 helicopters to Gomel, Belarus, on February 22. Russian social media users observed a likely reinforced Russian battalion tactical group in Novooskolsky Raion, Belgorod, Russia, on February 22. Satellite imagery observed growing Russian armor buildups in Belgorod and Valuyki, Russia, on February 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia began withdrawing all diplomatic staff from across Ukraine on February 23, indicating that Russia is preparing to conduct large combat operations against Ukraine. Russian officials stated that Russia began evacuating personnel from all diplomatic missions in Kyiv, Lviv, Kharkiv, and Odesa, Ukraine, on February 23. Russian officials confirmed that Russian diplomatic staff destroyed documents in Russian diplomatic missions in Ukraine on February 22. The Ukrainian Foreign Ministry (MFA) recommended that Ukrainian citizens in Russia leave Russia immediately on February 23. Russia will likely conduct offensive operations against Ukraine before February 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian Foreign Ministry (MFA) threatened an unspecified “strong and not necessarily symmetrical” response to US sanctions on February 23. The MFA added that sanctions are ineffective in preventing Russia from “firmly defending [Russian] interests.” MFA Spokesperson Maria Zakharova claimed the sanctions were “illegitimate” and targeted Russia’s development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin continued falsely accusing Ukrainian forces of attacking Russian territory on February 23 to legitimize additional Russian military action against Ukraine. The Russian Federal Security Service (FSB) claimed it prevented terrorist attacks on Crimean churches organized by the supporters of the “Right Sector” Ukrainian nationalist group on February 23. The FSB claimed it detained six Russian nationals that Right Sector radicalized online to detonate improved explosive devices. The Kremlin previously falsely accused Ukrainian forces of attacking the southern Russian city of Rostov with artillery and ground forces on February 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kremlin-sponsored TV channels denied Ukraine’s right to sovereignty over most of its territory from February 22 to 23, setting information conditions for the Russian population to support a large war against Ukraine beyond Donbas. Russian news program Vesti claimed that Russia cannot forget that Russian political leaders created the territory of modern Ukraine by robbing Russia of its “historical territories.” Vesti implied that only Kirovohrad and Dnipropetrovsk oblasts, and the northern parts of Zaporizhzhia and Mykolaiv oblasts, are legitimate Ukrainian territories, setting information conditions for the Russian population to support a Russian invasion and occupation of Ukraine. Vesti praised Putin’s February 21 speech, claiming it restored thousands of years to Russian history and that the Ukrainian nation did not exist during the Kievan Rus kingdom from the 9th to the mid-13th century. Vesti falsely claimed that the Kremlin recognized Ukraine as a sovereign state and agreed to pay Ukraine’s perestroika debts in 1991 under an agreement that Ukraine would return Russian “territorial gifts” to Russia. Vesti accused Ukraine of “blowing its chance” to finally create a state by falling under the control of radical nationalists and the West. Russian talk show Vremya Pokazhet additionally stated that Putin’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) marked the return of “Russian sovereignty,” implying that Ukrainian territories are Russian territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin intensified offensive cyber operations against Ukrainian government websites, Ukrainian frontline soldiers, and open-source intelligence (OSINT) Russia-watchers on February 23. Likely Russian actors conducted Distributed Denial-of-Service (DDoS) cyberattacks against Ukraine’s Foreign Ministry, Defense Ministry, Cabinet of Ministers, Parliament, Federal Security Service, and banks on February 23. Likely Russian electronic warfare systems sent targeted propaganda text messages to personnel of Ukraine’s 53rd and 54th mechanized brigades near the frontline informing the servicemen that Russian units deployed to Donbas with Moscow’s approval to attack on February 22. The messages called on Ukrainian servicemen to desert their posts to save their lives — a psychological warfare tactic that Russian forces previously used in 2015. Likely Russian Twitter bots also mass-reported OSINT aggregators that study Russian military movements on Twitter, temporarily disabling at least five prominent OSINT accounts for 12 hours on February 22-23. Increased Russian cyberattacks and electronic warfare activity are leading indicators of an imminent Russian attack against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin continued to justify its recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) as liberating the DNR and LNR from Ukrainian oppression to legitimize further military action in Ukraine. The State Duma Committee’s First Deputy Chairman Viktor Vodolatsky claimed that Ukrainian aggression makes it “impossible” for LNR and DNR residents evacuated to Russia to return to Ukraine. Senior United Russia official Andrey Turchak announced that the Duma will form a friendship group with the DNR and LNR parliaments on February 23, further formalizing institutional ties. Turchak said on February 23 that Russia will only send troops into the DNR and LNR if the republics’ leadership requests such action; the proxies requested Russian troops later on February 23. The Russian Foreign Ministry (MFA) denied that Russian President Vladimir Putin’s recognition of the LNR and DNR violates the Minsk II Accords on February 23. The MFA stated that Kyiv has violated the Minsk II Accords since 2014 by committing ”hallmarks of genocide” against citizens of Donbas and called on the United Nations to demand that the government of Ukraine implement the agreements. Russian Representative to the UN Vasily Nebeznya stated that Russia will not be lenient with violators of the ceasefire in Donbas on February 23. Nebeznya said the West is inciting Ukrainian aggression and urged the UN General Assembly to calm Kyiv’s offensive military action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republic (DNR and LNR) heads Denis Pushilin and Leonid Pasechnik asked Russian President Vladimir Putin to deploy Russian Armed Forces to Donbas on February 23, setting conditions for an immediate deployment of Russian ground forces at scale into Donbas. Pushilin and Pasechnik called on Putin to repel Ukrainian aggression in Donbas and officially invoked provisions in the treaties of “friendship, cooperation and mutual Assistance” that Russia ratified on February 22. Pushilin falsely claimed that Kyiv continues to wage genocide against DNR residents while Pasechnik falsely claimed that Western states support Ukraine forcibly capturing the LNR’s territory. Putin will likely overtly deploy Russian forces to Donbas at scale on February 24 to set conditions for future military operations to conquer the entire Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts and possibly support the invasion of the rest of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) claimed that they cannot currently expand their borders without Russia’s help to overcome Ukrainian forces on February 22-23, setting conditions for Russia to undertake offensive operations to capture all of Donetsk and Luhansk Oblasts. DNR Head Denis Pushilin claimed that the DNR cannot consider expanding its territorial control through the entire Donetsk oblast because Ukrainian forces could launch an offensive “at any moment.” Pushilin reiterated claims that Ukrainian forces deployed multiple launch rocket systems to the front line. The LNR claimed that Ukrainian forces intensified artillery attacks against civilians in Donbas and killed an LNR militant. The Kremlin continued coordinating support for the proxies’ claims. The Russian Investigative Committee claimed on February 23 that it identified at least 85 Ukrainian servicemembers and officials who committed “crimes” or “gave criminal orders” in combat in Donbas. The DNR and LNR escalated kinetic activity against Ukraine while making these claims and killed at least one Ukrainian soldier from February 22 to 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ukrainian-activity&quot;&gt;Ukrainian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ukrainian government announced conscription of reservists, declared a state of emergency, and approved martial law protocols on February 22-23 in response to Russian President Vladimir Putin acquiring the legal authority to deploy troops abroad. Ukrainian Commander-in-Chief Valery Zaluzhny ordered the conscription of reservists for up to one year on February 23. Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky emphasized on February 22 that Ukraine has not announced a general mobilization. Ukraine’s parliament and the National Security and Defense Council both unanimously declared a state of emergency in all Ukrainian regions except Donetsk and Luhansk Oblasts because similar regimes already exist there. Ukraine’s parliament also adopted protocols for government operation during a state of emergency and/or martial law, voted to increase defense spending by over 900 million dollars, and supported introducing sanctions against Russian MPs who voted for the recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics. Ukrainian National Police Deputy Chairman Oleksandr Fatsevich stated that law enforcement will continue to guard over 100 energy facilities and other unspecified critical infrastructure. The Ukrainian Border Service announced restrictions on civilian traffic and sea movements and other activities in regions bordering Russia, Belarus, Crimea, and non-government-controlled Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States announced on February 22 it will forward-deploy 5,000 additional US forces to Europe and that it has repositioned US forces in Europe eastward to deter Russian aggression and support US allies. US Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin announced troop movements in Romania, Bulgaria, Hungary, Poland, and Germany on February 22. The 18th Airborne Corps moved a headquarters capable of commanding a Joint Task Force to Germany. The Defense Department noted that these forces are trained and equipped to deter aggression and defend US allies. Austin announced on February 22 that the United States deployed 4,700 personnel of the 82nd Airborne Division and unspecified support elements from the United States to Germany. Austin also announced that the 82nd Airborne Division deployed an Infantry Combat Brigade and unspecified support elements to Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US intelligence reportedly assessed on February 23 that Russia deployed initial forces into Donbas and will conduct a full-scale invasion of Ukraine within the next 48 hours (by February 25). Anonymous US officials told Newsweek that the Biden Administration informed Ukraine that Russia will likely conduct a “full-scale” invasion of Ukraine within the next 48 hours and that a possible Russian surveillance aircraft violated Ukrainian airspace on February 23. Newsweek added that Russia will likely employ airstrikes, cruise missiles, and a ground invasion. Pentagon spokesperson John Kirby said Russian forces along Ukraine’s border are “at a state of readiness where they could attack at any time” during a February 23 press briefing. Kirby said that Russian President Vladimir Putin has not indicated that he is willing to de-escalate. Kirby and Latvian Prime Minister Arturs Krišjānis Kariņš claimed Russia moved additional forces and tanks into Ukrainian territory controlled by the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics in Donbas on February 23. A senior US official told CNN on February 23 that Russia deployed one to two battalion tactical groups, each made up of around 800 Russian troops, to Donbas. US officials told CNN and Newsweek on February 23 that Russian forces may attack the northeastern Ukrainian city of Kharkiv, which Ukraine does not plan to evacuate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US and allied leaders followed through on their promises to cancel meetings with top Russian officials as Russia began its invasion of proxy-occupied eastern Ukraine. US Secretary of State Antony Blinken canceled a planned February 24 meeting in Geneva with Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov on February 22, citing Russia’s invasion of Ukraine and wholesale rejection of diplomacy. Italian Foreign Minister Luigi Di Maio also announced Italy will not hold meetings with Russian officials until Russia eases tensions on February 23. US President Joe Biden will likely not meet with Russian President Vladimir Putin as Biden had agreed to ”in principle” on February 21 barring additional Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-and-eu-activity&quot;&gt;NATO and EU Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western states announced sanctions against Russia on February 22 and 23, following similar actions by the United States, United Kingdom, the European Union (EU) on February 22. The Australian government sanctioned eight members of the Russian Security Council and several Russian banks and restricted trade with the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 23. The Canadian government sanctioned two Russian banks, banned Canadians from purchasing Russian sovereign debt, and sanctioned the DNR and LNR and Russian MPs who voted to recognize them on February 22. The Japanese government froze assets of Russian MPs involved in the recognition of the DNR and LNR and prohibited the sale of Russian bonds in Japan on February 23. The EU announced sanctions against Russian Defense Minister Sergei Shoigu and other senior Russian officials, as well as Russia’s Internet Research Agency, on February 23. The EU said this would be the first of many installments of sanctions should Russia continue to take aggressive action against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union (EU) and the United States are likely leveraging Russia’s unprecedented aggression against Ukraine as a catalyst to transition the EU away from its current dependence on Russian natural gas. Russia has previously used its control over natural gas imports into eastern Europe to pressure EU member states and Ukraine. The Washington Post reported on February 23 that the European Commission will announce plans to transition the EU away from dependence on Russian natural gas and bolster the EU’s resiliency against price spikes and supply disruptions on March 2. The plan would require the EU to fill natural gas reserves annually before winter. The plan would also call for a 40 percent reduction in the EU’s fossil fuel consumption by 2030. Germany will likely back the proposal given it agreed to pause its Nord Stream 2 pipeline project on February 22, moving away from its previously close relationship with Russian energy companies. US President Joe Biden announced new sanctions on the company building the Nord Stream 2 pipeline, a subsidiary of the Russian state-owned Gazprom, on February 23. German Economic Minister Robert Habeck stated that Germany could get natural gas imports without Russia if necessary on February 23. The United Kingdom also announced on February 17 that it would provide £100 million over the next three years to supplement Ukraine’s energy sector and reduce Ukraine’s dependency on Russian gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom increased its economic and military support packages to Ukraine to deter and mitigate Russian aggression on February 23. UK Foreign Secretary Liz Truss announced a new economic package to support Ukraine’s economic stability on February 23. The UK guaranteed Multilateral Development Bank (MDB) loans to Ukraine to mitigate the effects of Russia’s continued aggression against Ukraine on February 23. Truss also stated that ”nothing is off the table” in a UK response to Russia’s aggression on February 23. UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson announced the UK provision of additional military aid to Ukraine including unspecified defensive weapons and non-lethal aid on February 23. UK Culture Secretary Nadine Dorries asked UK media regulators to review Russia’s state-owned news channel RT’s broadcasting license and officially accused the channel of being a Kremlin disinformation tool on February 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan remains determined to balance between Russia and Ukraine despite NATO sanctions and pressure over Black Sea access. Erdogan reiterated that Turkey does not accept Russia’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR), called for a return to the Minsk II Accords, and stated that Turkey follows a ”constructive approach” within NATO in a February 23 phone call with Russian President Vladimir Putin. Erdogan called for swift and decisive NATO action, criticized Western leaders’ previous ineffective diplomatic efforts to meet with the Kremlin, and stated that Turkey cannot abandon its ties with Russia or Ukraine due to Turkey’s strong economic, military, and political ties with both states in a February 23 interview. The Turkish government has so far refrained from imposing sanctions on Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, Ukrainian Ambassador to Turkey Vasyl Bodnar told Reuters on February 23 that Ukraine may ask Turkey to prevent the passage of Russian vessels into the Black Sea if Russia launches a full-scale invasion. Turkey controls and regulates passage through its two straits between the Mediterranean and Black Seas under the 1936 Montreux Convention. The Convention guarantees passage to warships and civilian vessels within certain regulations “during peacetime.” However, Turkey can choose to close the straits to all foreign warships in “war time or when it is threatened by aggression.” Ankara will likely allow the passage of Russian vessels throughout Russia’s ongoing conflict with Ukraine, barring direct Russian aggression against Turkey or NATO, to avoid a direct and costly confrontation with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson Hua Chunying criticized Western sanctions on Russia, stated that China will not impose sanctions, and rejected any comparison between Ukraine and Taiwan on February 23. Hua Chunying criticized Western sanctions as “illegal” and called for international dialogue and negotiations instead. Hua Chunying added that China sees sanctions-oriented policies as ineffective and that previous US sanctions caused “serious economic difficulties and impacted people’s livelihood” and the United States should not undermine the rights and interests of China and other parties. Hua Chunying rejected any comparison between Ukraine and Taiwan, claiming Taiwan has always been an “inalienable part” of China. UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson had implied that a Russian takeover of Ukraine would allow China to conclude that “might makes right” and endanger Taiwan during a February 19 speech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 22-23.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/22</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-22-ukraine-conflict-update-5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/22" /><published>2022-02-22T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-22T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-22-ukraine-conflict-update-5.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 21-22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin recognized the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics as covering the entirety of Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts (provinces) and secured unrestricted formal parliamentary authorization to deploy Russian forces abroad on February 22, setting conditions for a further offensive against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The US and its European allies defined Putin’s recognition of the DNR and LNR as an invasion of Ukraine and imposed a first round of sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ukraine called for further sanctions on Russia and Western military support, stressing its readiness to resist further Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Russia’s allies declined to immediately recognize the DNR and LNR and Russia faced widespread international condemnation.
T&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;he Russian stock market and Rouble plummeted as the Kremlin sought to reassure Russia’s population that Russia can weather Western sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US redeployed existing forces in Europe to support Eastern European allies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin likely continued to deploy forces to Donbas but has not yet announced overt deployments on February 22. Reuters reported locating five unmarked tanks in the Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) on February 22. Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitry Peskov did not confirm the presence of Russian troops in Donbas but emphasized that all developments in Donbas would be oriented around saving the lives of Russian citizens from Ukrainian aggression. The Russian Foreign Ministry stated Russia may establish military bases in Donbas under cooperation treaties with DNR and LNR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian social media users observed an estimated two battalions, likely of the Russian 4th Tank Division, heading toward a likely assembly area near Golovchino, Belgorod, Russia, on February 21. Russian 1st Tank Army elements in Golovchino are likely postured against the Velyka Pysarivka-Okhtyrka axis and could support efforts to envelop Kharkiv or cut Ukrainian forces in southern and eastern Ukraine off from Kyiv. Russian social media users additionally observed that Russian vehicle formations near Ukraine’s borders are using at least three different tactical markings as of February 22; vehicles are marked in paint with the letter “Z,” circular markings, and triangular markings. These markers could indicate different task forces within a larger formation or echelon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin recognized the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics as covering the entirety of Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts (provinces) and secured unrestricted formal parliamentary authorization to deploy Russian forces abroad on February 22. Considerable parts of those oblasts remain in Ukrainian control with the heavily fortified “line of contact” running through both and Putin will need to seize them militarily to make good on his recognition of the DNR and LNR claims to them. Russia’s Federation Council, the Russian senate, additionally approved an authorization for Putin to use Russian forces abroad. The authorization stipulates no restrictions on the size, timing, duration, or purpose of Russian military operations abroad. Putin’s speech and the Federation Council’s authorization today significantly increases the likelihood of a Russian military operation into unoccupied eastern Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin falsely claimed Ukraine abandoned the Minsk II Accords, and replaced the accord’s demands of Ukraine with his own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognize Russia’s annexation of Crimea;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formally renounce all aspirations to join NATO;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter peaceful negotiations with the LNR and DNR; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Demilitarize,” with no set demands other than claiming Russia must monitor Ukraine’s “nuclear ambitions.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin’s demands and recognition of DNR and LNR claims to Ukrainian-held territory is a soft declaration of war against Ukraine. Putin will likely continue to phase his operations — gauging Ukrainian and Western responses to his February 22 speech before initiating his next course of action. Putin will likely seize the remainder of the Ukrainian-controlled Donetsk and Luhansk Oblasts, probably through a mechanized invasion accompanied by an air and missile campaign across unoccupied Ukraine as ISW has previously forecasted. He can choose various pretexts for such an attack depending on the informational conditions he can set in the coming hours and days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senior Kremlin officials justified Russia’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) as necessary to protect Russian citizens and falsely claimed Ukrainian aggression on February 22. The Russian Foreign Ministry (MFA) stated that Russia recognized the DNR and LNR because Kyiv abandoned the Minsk II Accords and sought to solve the conflict in Donbas with force. Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov accused the West of “Russophobia” in not recognizing the DNR and LNR. State Duma International Affairs Committee Chairman Leonid Slutsky stated that recognition is necessary for preserving the ”Russian World,” Russian language, and Russian culture. Deputy Chairman of the Russian Security Council Dmitry Medvedev said that Russia had “no right” to “abandon” the 800,000 Russian citizens living in Donbas. Russian Ambassador to the United Nations Vasily Nebenzya stated that Kyiv deployed 120,000 troops near Donbas and insinuated that Western security assistance to Ukraine threatened the population in Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin sought to downplay the likely negative effects of Western sanctions to the Russian population and international markets on February 22. The Moscow Exchange Index fell by 10.5 percent and the ruble plunged to 80 against the US dollar after Russian President Vladimir Putin recognized the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics on February 21. The Russian Central Bank announced measures to support Russian financial markets amid these ruble and Russian stock depreciations on February 22. Russian state wire TASS misreported that Russian state-owned Sberbank’s share value increased on February 22, when Sberbank’s share value actually decreased. Senior Kremlin officials issued nationalist rhetoric claiming that Russia is impervious to sanctions on February 22. Deputy Chairman of the Russian National Security Council Dmitry Medvedev posted a vitriolic tweet warning that Europeans will pay 2,000 euros per 1,000 cubic meters of gas after German Chancellor Olaf Scholtz announced that Germany will halt the certification of the Nord Stream 2 gas pipeline. TASS reported that Russian Deputy Foreign Minister Andrey Rudenko stated Russia is “not afraid of anything,” including what TASS called “anti-Russian sanctions.” The Kremlin likely seeks to mitigate the domestic discontent likely to follow the imposition of Western sanctions on Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian Foreign Ministry announced on February 22 it will evacuate Russia’s foreign missions in Ukraine “in the very near future” due to claimed Russophobia and nationalist threats; the evacuation is likely primarily driven by Russian plans for further military operations. The Russian Foreign Ministry also announced it will establish diplomatic relations with Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics. Social media users also reported noticing Russian consulate staff burning documents in both Odesa and Kyiv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) reiterated claims they should rightfully control all territory in Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts and continued to accuse Ukrainian forces of attacking Donbas on February 22. DNR and LNR authorities reiterated 2014 claims that their polities should control the entire territory of the Donetsk and Luhansk oblasts, respectively, on February 22. A senior LNR official demanded Ukrainian troops withdraw from Ukrainian government-controlled Luhansk Oblast on February 22. DNR officials accused Ukrainian forces of firing multiple launch rocket systems against the DNR for the first time since 2018 on February 22. The LNR accused Ukrainian forces of killing one LNR serviceman with artillery on February 22. DNR officials accused Ukrainian saboteurs of conducting a car bomb terrorist attack that killed three DNR citizens on February 22. DNR authorities ordered the conscription of all eligible DNR citizens born from 1995-2004 who are not yet in the DNR’s reserve and began organizing “special formations” for unspecified combat missions on February 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin continued evacuating women and children from Donbas on February 22 to create the false narrative of a Ukrainian “genocide” against Donbas. Russian authorities claim Russia has accepted over 90,000 refugees from Donbas and that approximately 30 Russian provinces plan to host refugees as of February 22. Russia’s Prosecutor General’s Office announced it formed mobile reception centers in eight Russian regions for evacuated DNR and LNR residents. Rostov Oblast has become a major refugee hub in particular; Rostov’s regional government announced that DNR and LNR citizens in Rostov are eligible for “forced migrant“ status or temporary asylum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian allies did not recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 22 after Russian President Vladimir Putin’s decree for immediate recognition. The Belarusian Foreign Ministry stated it “respected and understood” the Kremlin’s decision to recognize the independence of DNR and LNR given rising Western provocations in Eastern Europe but did not recognize the proxy republics. Kazakhstan’s Foreign Ministry asserted its neutrality and did not recognize the territories but noted that Kazakhstan is currently developing its official position. Syrian Foreign Minister Faisal Mikdad claimed that Syria wants to recognize the DNR and LNR “as early as possible” through the Syrian parliament to strengthen long-standing relations with the republics. Abkhazian officials praised DNR and LNR leadership for obtaining international recognition. Other Russian proxy republics will likely recognize the DNR and LNR in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ukrainian-activity&quot;&gt;Ukrainian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian officials decried Russian President Vladimir Putin’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR), called for immediate sanctions on Russia, and called for calm in Ukraine on February 21-22. Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky stated that DNR and LNR recognition may create a legal basis for further Russian aggression against Ukraine but maintained that Russia will not conduct a full-scale invasion. Zelensky and Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba stated that Putin’s decision required an immediate response from allies and sanctions. Zelensky and the Ukrainian Foreign Ministry (MFA) sent a request to United Nations (UN) member states to hold immediate consultations with the 1994 Budapest Memorandum signatories. Zelensky stated that the MFA sent him a request to sever diplomatic relations with Russia. Ukraine’s parliament called on the international community to block Nord Stream-2, to disconnect Russia from the SWIFT international banking system, and ban Russian technology and military imports. Leaders of the Ukrainian ruling party Servant of the People told MPs not to leave Kyiv for the next two weeks. The Ukrainian Armed Forces increased their readiness and stressed the need for calm. Ukrainian Defense Minister Oleksiy Reznikov stated Ukraine might experience losses and fear but will be triumphant against Putin’s desire to reunite the Soviet Union. The Ukrainian Defense Ministry refuted Kremlin-sponsored media claims that the Ukrainian Armed Forces shelled a Russian border checkpoint in the Rostov Oblast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White House expanded sanctions against Russia and the Donetsk (DNR) and Luhansk (LNR) People’s Republics on 22 February, altering the February 21 White House’s statement that Russia’s recognition of its proxies did not count as an invasion. US President Joe Biden stated that Russia’s aggression is the ”beginning of an invasion of Ukraine” in a televised address on February 22. Biden announced new sanctions on two Russian financial institutions and confirmed the halt of Nord Stream 2‘s certification process on February 22 –marking a shift from the White House’s February 21 stance on Russian deployments to Donbas. US Secretary of State Antony Blinken echoed Biden’s comments and reaffirmed the US’ support for Ukraine in a call with Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba on February 21. Blinken emphasized President Putin’s decision calls for a swift and firm response and emphasized the United States will take appropriate actions alongside its allies. Biden also met with Kuleba before announcing sanctions against Russia in Washington on February 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Joe Biden authorized additional deployments of troops, jets, and helicopters in Europe to strengthen allies and defend NATO on February 22. A US defense official specified that the United States will move F-35 fighter jets, Apache helicopters, and approximately 800 troops already in Europe to the Baltic states, Romania, and Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CNN cited anonymous US officials saying that the US discussed options with Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky to travel from Kyiv to Lviv, in Western Ukraine, if Russia continues to escalate on February 21. The White House said that it is Zelensky’s decision to relocate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-and-eu-activity&quot;&gt;NATO and EU Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union condemned Russian President Vladimir Putin’s decision to recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) and Russian deployments to these areas on February 22. The EU stated that Russia’s decision violates international law and agreements, including UN Security Council Resolution 2202 and the Minsk Agreements. The EU called on Russia to reverse its decision and uphold its commitments to work within the Normandy format and the Trilateral Contact Group (TCG). The EU said it will impose economic sanctions on Russia for violating Ukrainian sovereignty and warned of additional political and economic sanctions should Russia use the recognition as a pretext for taking further military action against Ukraine. EU states — including Germany, Poland, Italy, Romania, Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia — also issued individual statements condemning Russia’s actions as a violation of Ukraine’s territorial integrity. EU Foreign Ministers discussed specific sanctions against Russia, including Russian banks and individuals involved in recognizing the DNR and LNR, to limit Russia’s access to European capital and financial markets on February 22. No readouts have been published on this meeting as of 4:30 pm ET.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO-Ukraine Commission held an extraordinary meeting to address the security situation in Ukraine on February 22. NATO condemned Russian President Vladimir Putin’s decision to recognize the independence of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) but said that diplomacy is still an option, echoing the European Union’s response. NATO warned that Russian forces are “ready to strike” and that NATO will do whatever is necessary to defend Ukraine from Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G7 foreign ministers agreed on a sanctions package against Russia and reiterated support for Ukraine in a joint phone call on February 22. UK Foreign Secretary Liz Truss announced that the foreign ministers agreed on a “strong package of coordinated escalatory sanctions” in response to Russia’s violation of its “international commitments.” The G7 is comprised of the United States, United Kingdom, Germany, Canada, Japan, Italy, and France. The foreign ministers did not issue further details as of February 22, 5:00 pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-organization-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Organization Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) condemned Russia’s decision to recognize the Donetsk (DNR) and Luhansk (LNR) People’s Republic and order troops to Ukraine during an emergency session on February 21. The US, UK, and Ukraine said that Russia’s decision is a violation of Ukrainian territorial integrity and Ukrainian sovereignty and violated international norms and agreements. Representatives from China and India called for all parties to exercise restraint and to seek mutually amicable solutions, breaking from other member states’ full condemnation of Russia’s actions. Russian Ambassador to the UN Vasily Nebenzya said that UNSC member states should, “not make the situation worse” and that Russia would continue to concentrate on “how to avoid war.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German Chancellor Olaf Scholz announced Germany will pause the authorization of Russia’s Nord Stream 2 natural gas pipeline on February 22. Germany’s temporary pause will harm the Kremlin’s European energy policy. Scholz’s decision is reversible if the EU assesses a greater energy need or diplomatically favorable conditions to continue with the project in the coming months, however. The US and UK supported Germany’s decision to halt certification. Russian Security Council Deputy Chairman Dmitry Medvedev threatened a severe increase in natural gas prices for Europe in response to Scholz’s announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK imposed a first round of sanctions against Russia on February 22. UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson sanctioned five Russian government-run banks (Rossiya, IS Bank, GenBank, Promsvyazbank, and Black Sea Bank), several oligarchs and businesspeople with close ties to Russian President Vladimir Putin, and Russian Duma and Federation Council members who voted to recognize the DNR and LNR. UK officials reiterated their commitment to Ukraine’s sovereignty and warned that Russia may be laying the groundwork for a full-scale invasion of Ukraine. The UK will extend its standing territorial sanctions on Russian-occupied Crimea to the DNR and LNR. UK Foreign Secretary Liz Truss threatened further sanctions on the Russian financial sector, Russian oligarchs, and businesses to prevent Russian access to sovereign debt on UK markets and isolate Russia from the global economy if the Kremlin continues with its escalation in Ukraine. lvi The UK called on Russia to withdraw its troops from Ukraine, meet its obligations under the UN Charter, and fulfill the commitments it made under the Helsinki Final Act, the Minsk Agreement, and the 1994 Budapest Memorandum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hungarian Defense Minister Tibor Benko announced that Hungary will deploy an unspecified number of troops to its eastern border with Ukraine on February 22. Benko said that Hungary must prepare for “every eventuality, including humanitarian tasks and border protection.” He announced that Hungary will prepare for the arrival of Ukrainian refugees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson and French President Emmanuel Marcon condemned Russia’s “blatant attack on freedom and democracy” in a February 22 call. Johnson and Macron agreed that they must continue to work together to target Russian individuals and entities who finance Russian President Vladimir Putin’s actions. They reiterated that the UK and France will continue to defend European security against Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey rejected Russia’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) and reiterated support for Ukraine but remains wary of imposing sanctions against Russia. Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky held a phone call on February 22. President Zelensky suggested including Turkey, Ukraine, and Germany in a summit with the United Nations Security Council’s permanent members. Erdogan emphasized that Russia’s recognition of the DNR and LNR is unacceptable and stressed the need for diplomacy in a statement after the call. The Turkish Foreign Ministry issued a similar statement on February 21 that classified Russia’s actions as a clear violation of Ukraine’s territorial integrity but refrained from calling for sanctions against Russia — a break from most NATO allies’ sanctions-oriented approach. Turkey still seeks to maintain close defense and diplomatic ties with Ukraine but likely wants avoid a possible retaliatory response from Russia and the spillover financial impact of Russia-targeted sanctions. Turkish Presidential Advisor Ibrahim Kalin recommended against sanctions in an earlier statement on February 19. Erdogan also cut short his three-day Africa trip and returned to Turkey on February 22 — likely in response to recent Russian escalations in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi called on all parties involved in the worsening Ukraine conflict to show restraint in a phone call with US Secretary of State Antony Blinken on February 22. Wang Yi’s abstention from taking a hardline stance on the issue likely signals China’s reluctance to harm its already deteriorating ties with the West nor its growing relationship with Moscow. Wang Yi said the security concerns of any country must be respected and urged the involved parties to resolve differences through dialogue. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Wang Wenbin reiterated Wang Yi‘s statements during a briefing on February 22 and said China will contact all involved parties “based on the merits of the matter.” Chinese ambassador the United Nations Zhang Jun echoed Wang Yi and Wang Wenbin’s messaging in an emergency meeting of the UN Security Council on February 22. Zhang Jun said that all parties must exercise restraint and avoid any action that may fuel tensions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 21-22.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/21</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-21-ukraine-conflict-update-4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/21" /><published>2022-02-21T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-21-ukraine-conflict-update-4.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 20-21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian troops began overtly deploying to occupied Donbas following Putin’s recognition of the independence of Russia’s proxy Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putin gave a maximalist speech denying Ukrainian sovereignty and its right to exist as an independent state, justifying further Russian offensive action and indicating the Kremlin is unlikely to stop in Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The White House and Western states did not recognize Russia’s overt deployment of troops into Ukraine as an “invasion” but condemned Putin’s recognition of the DNR and LNR and announced limited sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Russian government falsely accused Ukrainian forces of attacking Russian territory for the first time in the current crisis, setting conditions for Russia to legitimize further military action against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The United States warned the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights of a Russian “kill list” of politicians and likely future dissidents for Russia to target during a Russian occupation of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia began deploying troops to Donbas, likely from the 8th Combined Arms Army, following Russian President Vladimir Putin’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 21. Independent Russian news wire Interfax reported that DNR residents observed two unidentified armored-vehicle columns moving in DNR during the early morning of February 22. Social media users in the DNR claimed they observed Russian forces entering Donetsk during the evening of February 21-22. Online traffic monitoring data showed that traffic slowed in Ivanovo-Yasinovka, Rostov Oblast, (approximately 10 kilometers from the Russian-Ukrainian border) in the evening on February 21. Russian forces deploying into Donbas may have created this additional traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unspecified elements of Russia’s Strategic Rocket Forces (nuclear weapons) continued conducting readiness training and exercises on February 20. Servicemen trained on mobile ground missile systems and practiced operating communication systems at the Kapustin Yar Training Ground and two other training centers in Pereslavl-Zalessky, Yaroslavl Oblast, and Ostrov, Peskov Oblast. Additional unspecified elements of the Strategic Rocket Forces conducted unspecified combat training with simulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian forces near Ukraine, including the 4th Tank Division, continued to deploy to staging grounds on the Ukrainian border on February 20 and 21. Satellite imagery observed Russian forces at the Soloti storage camp in Belgorod redeploy south to the Ukrainian border on February 20. Russian social media users observed a likely battalion tactical group of the 4th Tank Division equipped with T-80U tanks redeploying to an unknown location from Belgorod, Russia. Satellite images observed a new Russian mobile field hospital in Shebekino, Belgorod Oblast, Russia, (approximately 5 kilometers from the Russian-Ukrainian border) on February 20. Satellite imagery also observed Russian helicopters in Belgorod for the first time on February 21. Russian social media users observed a prefabricated modular bridge that could support Russian river crossings in Ukraine in transit through Crimea on February 21. Unspecified Russian Southern Military District elements conducted river crossing exercises at the Prudboy Training Ground in Volgograd on February 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chechen Rosgvardia (Russian National Guard) forces deployed to southern Belarus, 30km from the Ukrainian border, on February 21. Belarusian social media users observed Russian National Guard elements from Chechnya in Yelsk, Belarus, for the first time on February 21. The Kremlin may intend to use Rosgvardia forces as an occupation force in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin formally recognized the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) and signed mutual cooperation treaties stipulating the deployment of Russian forces to Donbas following speeches attempting to justify Russian aggression against Ukraine on February 21. The Kremlin decreed that Russian troops will deploy to carry out “peacekeeping functions” in the DNR and LNR and that Russia will formally establish diplomatic relations and implement treaties of “friendship, cooperation and mutual Assistance” with the DNR and LNR. The Kremlin’s decision to recognize the DNR and LNR is a major strategic shift in the Kremlin’s approach to the war in Donbas and marks the Kremlin’s official departure from supporting the Minsk II Agreements — the legal basis of all ceasefires since 2015 and the basis that preserved Ukraine’s territorial integrity in Donbas. The Kremlin will overtly deploy military forces to Donbas and conduct overt military operations against Ukraine as ISW forecasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kremlin media aired a prerecorded Russian Security Council meeting the morning of February 21 to justify recognizing the DNR and LNR. Each member of the Security Council stated justifications for recognizing the DNR and LNR. Putin, Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov, and Kremlin Representative on Ukraine Dmitry Kozak all stated Ukraine never intended to implement and has abandoned the Minsk II Accords, with Lavrov adding the West will not force Ukraine to comply with the Minsk II Accords. Putin and Lavrov reiterated that NATO has refused to respond favorably to the Kremlin’s security demands on limiting NATO expansion. Kozak stated neither Ukraine nor the West “need” the Russian-occupied territory in Donbas and that Kyiv has a political interest in keeping the war in Donbas a frozen conflict. Russian Defense Minister Sergey Shoigu claimed intensifying Ukrainian attacks against the DNR and LNR created a humanitarian catastrophe, claiming that 90 percent of Donetsk residents have no water. Deputy Chairman of the Security Council Dmitry Medvedev argued the Kremlin should recognize the DNR and LNR despite the cost of Western sanctions, citing the Kremlin’s recognition of its proxies in Georgia in 2008. Putin attempted to frame the preplanned speeches as an unplanned meeting, likely to generate the perception of Kremlin buy-in to the recognition of the DNR and LNR, forcing key figures in the Russian government to publicly support his pre-planned action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin gave a speech prior to signing the decrees attacking the concept of Ukraine as a sovereign state, setting conditions for further Russian offensive action. Putin claimed Ukraine is an “integral part of [Russia’s] own history, culture, spiritual space” and was only created following the 1917 Russian Revolution. Putin claimed nationalists and oligarchic clans rule modern Ukraine and that the 2014 Euromaidan Revolution was a Western-backed coup. Putin claimed NATO can directly control Ukrainian forces to attack Russia and that NATO “cheated” its 1991 “promises” to not expand eastward. Putin claimed “Russia has done everything to preserve the territorial integrity of Ukraine” through the Minsk II Accords since 2015. Putin stated his decision to “immediately recognize the independence and sovereignty” of the DNR and LNR is “long overdue” and asked the Russian Federal Assembly to ratify the treaties “in the very near future,” which the Federal Assembly will likely do on February 22. Putin demanded that Ukraine immediately cease nonexistent hostilities against Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian government falsely accused Ukrainian forces of attacking Russian territory in Rostov with artillery and ground forces on February 21 to legitimize further military action against Ukraine. Russia’s Southern Military District claimed it destroyed two Ukrainian infantry fighting vehicles and killed five Ukrainian militants that crossed the border into Russian territory in Mityakinskaya, Rostov Oblast, on February 21. The Russian Federal Security Service (FSB) also claimed that Ukrainian artillery destroyed a Russian border checkpoint near Shcherbakovo, Rostov Oblast. FSB Director Alexander Bortnikov said that Russian forces captured one Ukrainian prisoner who participated in the attacks during the Russian Security Council meeting on February 21. Ukrainian government officials denied these falsely alleged attacks on February 21. The Kremlin will likely use these falsely claimed attacks to justify Russian military operations against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin amplified claims that Ukrainian aggression led to mass evacuations in the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 21. Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitry Peskov accused the Ukrainian Armed Forces of initiating provocations, endangering civilian lives, and intensifying shelling. Russian Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Maria Zakharova accused the West of encouraging Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky to denounce the Minsk II Accords and destroy Ukraine. Zakharova added that US Embassy in Moscow launched a “real information terrorist attack” aimed at frightening Russians about terrorist attacks in public places along the Ukrainian border and in large Russian cities. Russia’s Ministry of Emergency Situations and Russian Security Service (FSB) claimed 61,000 evacuees have entered Russia as of February 21. The Ministry announced that 43 regions can host up to 42,000 DNR and LNR evacuees. The Ministry claimed it has established about 400 temporary accommodation points and is developing an additional 149 points to accommodate up to 54,000 people. Russia’s Cabinet of Ministers allocated five billion rubles in payments to DNR and LNR evacuees on February 21. Russian Federation Council First Deputy Chairman Sergey Ryabukhin reiterated that financial aid to DNR and LNR residents will not negatively impact Russians residing within the Russian territory and will prevent the greater costs of a “humanitarian catastrophe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) claimed that Ukraine intensified its aggression through increased shelling and bombings targeting infrastructure and government buildings on February 20-21. The DNR and LNR most likely intensified their claims of Ukrainian aggression on February 20-21 to justify Russia’s formal recognition of the LNR and DNR as independent states and subsequent Russian military movements into DNR and LNR-held territory on February 21. The LNR and DNR repeatedly claimed that Ukrainian special forces saboteurs attempted to bomb critical infrastructure, most notably the LNR Joint Center for Control and Coordination (JCCC) and DNR artillery rocket and artillery depots, coal mines, water stations, electricity suppliers, and schools. The DNR also claimed that one Ukrainian soldier died while attempting to set up an explosive device at a Donetsk train station on February 21. The DNR and LNR claimed that Ukrainian shelling killed two LNR civilians, one DNR soldier, and one DNR civilian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Culture and Information Policy Minister Oleksandr Tkachenko said that Ukraine uncovered 10 fake reports of Ukraine-initiated aggression against the DNR and LNR on February 19-20 and reiterated that the Kremlin, DNR, and LNR are conducting a disinformation campaign to portray Ukraine as the aggressor in Donbas. CNN reported on February 21 that US forensic analysts said the metadata of the video portraying the February 11 alleged Ukrainian provocation in Donetsk shows the video was made three days before the claimed date of the event. DNR and LNR claims of Ukrainian aggression and provocations in Donbas are likely all coordinated and staged to falsely portray Ukraine as the aggressor in the rising conflict in Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;belarusian-activity&quot;&gt;Belarusian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belarusian Chief of the General Staff Viktor Gulevich reiterated that Russian forces deployed in Belarus will only leave Belarus and return to their bases in Russia “when there is an objective need” and demanded the United States and NATO states withdraw troops from near Belarusian borders on February 21. Gulevich also demanded that NATO let Belarus control NATO’s withdrawal through unspecified “verification measures.” Gulevich said that NATO’s eastern expansion is “aggressive and unjustified” and only increases the likelihood of armed conflict in Eastern Europe. Gulevich reiterated that Western military pressure against the Union State and “aggravation of the situation in Donbas” influenced the decision for Russian forces to remain in Belarus indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US officials condemned Russia’s recognition of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 21 but stated Russia’s overt deployment of forces to Donbas is not a new step, declining to state what the White House would consider a Russian “invasion” of Ukraine. US President Joe Biden signed an executive order to impose sanctions against investments, imports, and exports to the DNR and LNR. The White House emphasized that these sanctions — which are largely symbolic, as the United States has little to no trade with Russia‘s proxies — are separate from sanctions it is prepared to impose in response to a further Russian invasion of Ukraine. US National Security Adviser Jake Sullivan stated on February 21 that a Russian invasion of Ukraine could begin “in the coming hours or days” and would be “extremely violent.” US Ambassador to the OSCE Michael Carpenter condemned the Kremlin’s decision to recognize Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) and criticized the ”forced mobilization” of military-age male citizens in those regions. Several reporters quoted anonymous senior administration officials stating the White House does not view Russian forces operating overtly in Donbas as a new step triggering a US response. Putin will likely phase further offensive operations against Ukraine in part to diffuse Western responses to his operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York Times reported on February 20 that the United States intercepted Kremlin orders for Russian military units to “proceed with an invasion of Ukraine” the week before US President Joe Biden’s speech on February 18, while CNN separately reported the United States has not yet seen several indicators of a large-scale invasion. The New York Times additionally reported that US intelligence confirmed the Russian military has prepared to execute an unspecified attack plan and that 40-50 percent of units have shifted into combat formations. US intelligence officials separately told CNN that the United States still has not seen several “larger actions,” such as electronic jamming and cyberattacks, beyond previously seen tactical indicators. The Kremlin will likely pursue a phased operation and continue its military buildup throughout the week, rather than launching an immediate full-scale invasion of unoccupied Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Representative to the UN Bathsheba Nell Crocker warned the UN of a Russian “kill list” of Ukrainians to target following a potential invasion on February 20. Crocker claimed Russia has compiled a list of Ukrainians to kill or send to internment camps after invading Ukraine in a letter to UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Michelle Bachelet. Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitry Peskov denied the existence of the list on February 21. Crocker also warned that Russia will likely use lethal force to disperse potential Ukrainian protests or peaceful resistance to an occupation. Foreign Policy first reported on the US intelligence of a Russian ”kill list” on February 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Joe Biden agreed “in principle” on February 21 to meet with Russian President Vladimir Putin unless Russia invades Ukraine, though it is unclear as of publication if the White House considers Putin’s recognition of the DNR and LNR an invasion. French President Emmanuel Macron proposed Putin meet with Biden in a phone call with Putin on February 20. The Kremlin did not commit to the meeting. Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitri Peskov stated that Russia cannot make concrete summit plans while “tensions rise.” Peskov suggested that Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov and US Secretary of State Antony Blinken discuss plans for a summit during their planned February 24 meeting. The White House announced that any presidential meeting is contingent on Russia reducing its forces along the Ukrainian border. Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba welcomed diplomatic talks with Russia but requested that the other permanent United Nations Security Council members, Ukraine, Germany, and Turkey be included in a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Embassy in Moscow warned of possible Russian false flag attacks on public centers around Moscow, St. Petersburg, and the Ukrainian border on February 21. The US Embassy in Moscow warned individuals to avoid shopping centers, railway, and metro stations, and other public gathering locations. Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov stated in an interview that Russia had not seen proof to support the US claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-and-eu-activity&quot;&gt;NATO and EU Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several European leaders condemned the Kremlin’s decision to recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) as independent states and promised sanctions on Russia. Western leaders including Macron, NATO Secretary-General Jens Stoltenberg, German Chancellor Olaf Scholz, United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres, European Council President Charles Michel, and European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen condemned Putin’s decision to recognize the DNR and LNR as flagrantly violating the Minsk II Agreement on February 21. Michel and Leyen called the recognition ”illegal” and promised that the EU would impose sanctions against “those involved” in a joint statement. Putin informed Macron and Scholz separately over the phone that he planned to recognize the DNR and LNR prior to his public announcement, according to the Kremlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin likely seeks to drive a wedge between Western leaders and Ukraine by gradually increasing his aggression against Ukraine to introduce doubt into Western plans to impose sanctions in response to an “invasion.” Ukraine may perceive a lack of Western support if sanctions are not immediately imposed following the deployment of Russian “peacekeeping” forces into the DNR and LNR. No Western state has agreed to impose a planned package of “post-invasion” sanctions as of February 21. Leyen previously promised on February 20 that the EU would cut Russia off from international financial markets if it invades Ukraine. EU Foreign Affairs Chief Josep Borell said on February 21 that the EU has a sanctions package — including export limitations in key industries, freezing assets of Kremlin-friendly individuals, and an import ban on Russian oil and gas — that the EU can implement gradually “depending on the level of [Russia’s] aggression.” The EU also adopted a $1.36 billion “emergency support package” to Ukraine to mitigate the crisis’s detrimental effects on financial and economic stability during a meeting on February 21. During the meeting, Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba urged the EU to grant Ukraine a pathway to EU membership to send Russia a political message.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 20-21.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/qb7YYz4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/20</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-20-ukraine-conflict-update-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/20" /><published>2022-02-20T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-20T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-20-ukraine-conflict-update-3.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 19-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kremlin Spokesperson Peskov claimed Ukraine cannot and will not implement the Minsk II Accords, marking a significant change in Kremlin rhetoric that Russia could use as a pretext for further escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Belarusian Defense Minister announced Russian troops deployed in Belarus will remain in the country after the conclusion of Russian-Belarusian exercises — enabling an indefinite Russian military presence in Belarus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russia began testing its nuclear early warning system as part of ongoing exercises intended to deter any NATO response to Russian actions against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron proposed a renewed ceasefire (unsuccessfully, as of publication) in Donbas in back-to-back phone calls with Putin and Zelensky.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kremlin intensified its disinformation efforts to generate the false appearance of a Ukrainian genocide against Russians in Donbas through evacuation efforts and false claims of Ukrainian targeting of civilians.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A CBS national security correspondent claimed the US has intelligence that Russian commanders already received direct orders to invade Ukraine, but no US official confirmed the claim.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turkish officials decried the further imposition of sanctions on Russia and refrained from condemning Russia’s military buildup to retain its balancing relationship with the Kremlin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belarusian Defense Minister Viktor Khrenin announced Russian forces currently deployed to Belarus will remain there indefinitely during a press briefing about the conclusion of joint Russian-Belarusian “Union Resolve 2022” exercises on February 20. Khrenin stated that Russian President Vladimir Putin and Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko decided to “continue testing” Union State forces due to the “aggravation of the situation of Donbas.” Khrenin accused NATO and the West of “pumping up” states near the Union State — referring to Ukraine, Poland, and the Baltic States — with weapons, increasing their military posture against the Union State without advanced warning, and prioritizing “offensive means.” Khrenin accused the West of refusing to accept the Kremlin’s demanded “red lines” for the “security architecture of Europe.” Khrenin additionally parroted Russian Foreign Ministry rhetoric about the West undermining the “principle of the indivisibility of security” for the first time. Khrenin did not specify what Russian forces would remain in Belarus. Russian forces will likely permanently deploy to Belarus, as ISW has previously forecasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khrenin additionally outlined the outcomes of the exercises and stated that unified combat formations of Russian and Belarusian pilots, mechanized units, tank units, paratroopers, special forces, missilemen, and artillerymen operated with a high level of cooperation. Joint forces also addressed support issues and worked out an effective logical support system that enabled an effective Russian-Belarusian coalition. Khrenin praised the use of modern weapons systems and exchange of military expertise and experience between Russian and Belarusian troops. He thus concluded that “Union Resolve” achieved its intended goals and confirmed the cooperative capabilities of Russian and Belarusian forces in the face of Western pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s ballistic early warning network, the Russian 15th Aerospace Special Forces Army, began command and staff training in Moscow on February 20 as part of ongoing Russian nuclear exercises likely intended to deter a NATO response to any Russian offensive against Ukraine. Over 800 personnel from command, logistics, armaments, and other unspecified elements of the Titov Main Test and Space Systems Control Center, 820th Main Center for Missile Attack Warning, and the 821st Main Center for Reconnaissance of Situation in Space participated in the command and staff training. These elements comprise Russia’s early warning network against ballistic missile attacks. These exercises are likely part of the “GROM-2022” nuclear triad exercises that began on February 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s 49th Combined Arms Army of the Southern Military District (SMD) continued general readiness exercises on February 20. Unspecified regiment-sized (over 1,500 personnel) tank, motorized rifle, and artillery elements conducted company-level exercises at the Nikolo-Alexandrovsky Training Ground in Stavropol Krai. The elements conducted live fires with 152mm howitzers, multiple launch rocket systems, and T-72B3 tanks to destroy targets at distances of up to 4,000 meters. Reconnaissance, unmanned aerial vehicles (UAV), and signal elements of the SMD conducted support tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately 10 Russian Black Sea fleet ships, including the large landing ships “Novocherkassk,” “Saratov,” and “Tsezar Kunikov” passed through the Kerch Strait into the Sea of Azov on February 20. Russian Black Sea Fleet anti-submarine and patrol ships patrolled the Kerch Strait before moving to the Sea of Azov, according to local sources. Russian authorities issued a NOTAM (Notice to Air Missions) alert over the Sea of Azov for February 21-26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian social media users observed unspecified S-300 air defense elements in Kursk Oblast and Aleksandrovka, Belgorod Oblast heading towards Ukraine on February 19-20. The social media users observed at least 12 vehicles in Kursk Oblast on February 19 and 3 in Belgorod Oblast on February 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin intensified the tempo of the mass evacuations of women and children from the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) to Russia to generate the appearance of a genocide against Russians in Donbas between February 19 and February 20. Russia’s Emergency Situations Ministry stated that over 53,000 DNR and LNR residents evacuated to Russia as of February 20. The governors of Russia’s Voronezh, Kursk, and Ryazan oblasts declared states of emergency in response to refugee influxes on February 20. Rostov Oblast authorities stated that Rostov Oblast is prepared to receive approximately 14,000 refugees on February 20. At least six trains transported approximately 5,000 DNR and LNR residents to Russia on February 20. The Kremlin likely seeks to intensify its evacuation over the coming days. A prominent Russian Duma deputy from Rostov stated that 170,000 residents of the DNR and LNR are currently applying for Russian citizenship with Russian migration services on February 20. The Kremlin will likely use the claim of threats to civilians in Donbas to justify a Russian military deployment to Donbas or other, more serious military operations against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Deputy Foreign Minister Sergei Ryabkov claimed on February 20 that Western states are abandoning negotiations with Russia after the Kremlin only received two responses to 37 letters Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov sent to OSCE member states on January 28. Lavrov’s original letters demanded that individual Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE) member states respond to Russian security demands individually and not as a bloc, in a Kremlin attempt to undermine Western unity. Ryabkov claimed that the recipients of the letters are “leaving this conversation in a defiant way” by not responding to Russian demands. The European Union and NATO each submitted a collective response to the Kremlin that did not capitulate to core Russian demands on February 10. The Kremlin previously stated that Moscow would not accept a group response and that Moscow requires detailed responses from individual states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kremlin Spokesperson Dmitry Peskov claimed that Putin believes Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky “cannot, does not want [to], and will not” implement the Minsk II Accords in an interview on the Russia 1 TV channel on February 20. Peskov stated Ukraine’s only option is to directly negotiate with Russia’s proxies, the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR). Peskov denied Ukrainian statements that Moscow has refused to communicate with Ukrainian leadership. Peskov claimed that the Kremlin has asked Kyiv what Ukraine wished to discuss and did not receive a response. Peskov additionally stated that Western allegations of Russian plans to invade Ukraine have fueled tensions and that daily speculation of the date of an invasion “can have detrimental consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peskov’s statement on February 20 is a significant change in tone in Kremlin rhetoric about Ukraine’s intent to never implement the Minsk II Accords and is the closest the Kremlin has come to formally nullifying the Minsk II Accords. Kremlin messaging up to this point has emphasized that Ukraine seeks to sabotage the Minsk II Accords and has called on Ukraine to implement the accords, without explicitly stating that Ukraine “will not” implement these accords. The Kremlin could use the claim that Ukraine will never implement the Minsk II accords as a pretext for overtly deploying forces to the occupied Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) escalated their accusations of ongoing Ukrainian plans to attack Donbas on February 20. DNR claims from February 20 emphasized false threats about Ukrainian terrorist attacks against the DNR. The DNR claimed that it found and destroyed explosives caches belonging to Ukrainian sabotage groups, that it apprehended a “terrorist group” that sought to conduct explosive attacks against critical DNR civilian infrastructure, and that it recorded five sabotage attack attempts against the DNR since mid-February on February 20. The DNR reiterated accusations that the West is pushing Ukraine to attack Donbas, claiming that “Kyiv, with the approvals of the Westerners, began implementing the invasion plan for the [DNR’s] territory,” on February 20. LNR claims from February 20 emphasized an accusation that heavy Ukrainian shelling killed two LNR civilians. The Kremlin supported the LNR’s claims about Ukrainian forces killing two LNR civilians; Russia’s Investigative Committee announced that it would open a criminal investigation of “the Ukrainian Armed Forces’ crimes on the territory of Donbas” on February 20. The Kremlin may claim that Ukrainian forces “killed Russian citizens in Donbas” as a pretext to justify new Russian military operations against Ukraine as ISW previously forecasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ukrainian-activity&quot;&gt;Ukrainian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Permanent Representative to the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE) Yevhenii Tsymbaliuk on February 20 requested an extraordinary meeting of the OSCE Permanent Committee for February 21. Tsymbaliuk placed the request for the OSCE to discuss Russia’s military buildup near Ukraine and explore paths for de-escalation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US officials voiced continued concern Russia will likely invade unoccupied Ukraine but maintained that a diplomatic path is still possible in press engagements on February 20. Secretary of State Antony Blinken said Russia and Belarus’ continuing joint military exercises follow the Russian “playbook” of creating provocations to justify further escalations in an interview with CNN. Blinken noted the joint exercises and numerous false flag operations give “every indication” that Russian invasion plans are already in motion. Blinken and Vice President Kamala Harris underscored united international support for sweeping sanctions against Russia should an invasion occur, although Harris acknowledged some differences between NATO allies on the parameters of sanctions in a press conference. Blinken and Pentagon Press Secretary John Kirby separately reiterated that the United States has offered Putin several diplomatic options and will continue to peacefully attempt to deter and dissuade Russia until an invasion begins, including Blinken’s planned meeting with Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov on February 24. Blinken clarified that US recognition of Crimea or Eastern Ukraine as Russian territories is non-negotiable when asked during an interview on CBS’s Face the Nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CBS News national security correspondent David Martin reported that the US has intelligence that Russian commanders have received direct orders to proceed with an invasion of Ukraine on CBS’s Face the Nation on February 20. Martin said Russian commanders on the ground are making specific plans for how they would maneuver in their sectors of the battlefield. Martin emphasized that Russian commanders have received direct orders and are “doing everything that American commanders would do once they got the order to proceed.” No US official has publicly confirmed that Russian forces have received orders to invade as of February 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-organization-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Organization Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collective Security Treaty Organization (CSTO) Secretary General Stanislav Zas said the CSTO could “hypothetically” deploy peacekeepers to Donbas with Ukrainian consent, member state support, and a United Nations mandate in an interview with Reuters on February 17. Reuters published the interview with Zas on February 19. Reuters reported that Zas said that the CSTO has 17,000 personnel at “constant readiness,” a specialized “peacekeeping” force of approximately 4,000 personnel and that the CSTO can swiftly deploy the “needed” number of personnel to Ukraine immediately. Zas stated that only diplomacy can solve the Ukraine crisis. The Kremlin may frame a future overt Russian deployment to the occupied parts of eastern Ukraine as a “CSTO Peacekeeping mission.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron attempted to negotiate a ceasefire in Donbas through bilateral calls with Ukrainian President Zelensky and Russian President Putin on February 20. Macron and Putin discussed convening the trilateral contact group among the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE), Ukraine, and Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) to oversee a possible ceasefire in Donbas. Russia previously boycotted the two most recent OSCE meetings on February 18 and 19. The Kremlin readout stated that Putin and Macron also agreed to resume dialogue in the Normandy Format at the foreign ministry- and political advisors- levels. The Kremlin may slow down or later refuse to pursue a ceasefire if it assesses the negotiations as detrimental to its calculus, however. The Kremlin criticized NATO and Ukraine for pursuing a military solution, refusing to implement the Minsk II Accords, and claimed that Ukraine’s “intensifying shelling” necessitated civilian evacuations from the DNR and LNR to Russia. The French readout of Macron’s call with Zelensky stated Macron praised Ukraine’s restraint and that Zelensky reiterated his determination to respect the ceasefire by not reacting to Russian proxy provocations. Zelensky’s office did not issue a readout of the call with Macron as of February 20 at 3:30 EST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkish officials urged diplomatic talks and de-escalation on Ukraine instead of sanctions against Russia in several statements on February 19-20. Turkish Presidential Spokesperson Ibrahim Kalin stated that additional sanctions against Russia would undermine or delay a diplomatic solution in an interview with German newspaper Die Welt on February 19. Kalin criticized Russian President Vladimir Putin for seeking to redraw Russia‘s borders but urged states to listen to Russia and pursue mutual diplomacy, even if they do not fulfill Russian demands. Kalin also criticized Western and Russian statements for exacerbating tensions and recommended a flexible diplomatic approach — citing Turkey’s existing relations with Russia despite disagreements about Crimea and Libya. Kalin reiterated Turkey’s commitment to mediate between Russia and Ukraine both through NATO channels and bilaterally. Kalin additionally stated Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan will reiterate his offer to host Putin and Ukranian President Volodymyr Zelensky in Istanbul, Turkey, during a likely upcoming phone call on an unspecified date with Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, Turkish Chief of the General Staff Yasar Guler and NATO Supreme Allied Commander Europe Tod Wolters discussed recent developments in NATO over the phone on February 20. Prior to the call, Turkish Defense Minister Hulusi Akar urged caution against the risk of possible escalations due to disinformation campaigns and underlined the need for stability in the Black Sea region in a speech. Akar attended the Munich Security Conference in Munich, Germany on February 18-19 but his official agenda and Turkish meeting readouts did not focus on Ukraine. Ankara has recently played down the Russian military buildup compared to other NATO allies, likely due to its fragile partnership with Russia. It has not urged its citizens to leave Ukraine as of February 20 and limited its official statements on Ukraine after the most recent escalations near the Ukrainian border despite its ongoing defense cooperation with Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Foreign Secretary Liz Truss announced the UK will establish a new anti-disinformation center against Russia during an interview with the Daily Mail on February 19. Truss stated the UK’s “Russia-Ukraine Government Information Cell (GIC)” will expose disinformation and rebut false narratives. Truss warned that Russian disinformation campaigns have doubled in the past week and may serve as a false flag excuse for Russia to invade Ukraine. Truss stated the new GIC unit is the first revival of the UK’s original information units that it disbanded after the Cold War. Truss also warned that Russia’s invasion of Ukraine may encourage the Kremlin to pursue similar stated ambitions against other eastern European and Baltic states, including NATO allies. Truss also criticized the coordinated Chinese-Russian pressure against the right of new states to freely join NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson highlighted the potential human cost of a Russian attack on Ukraine, stated the US and UK could suspend Russian companies from trading in pounds and dollars and underscored NATO’s resoluteness should Russia invade in an interview with the BBC on February 20. Johnson claimed a Russian invasion has “in some senses begun.” Johnson said that western intelligence sources believe Russia intends to encircle the Ukrainian capital Kyiv in what would be “the biggest war in Europe” since World War II. Johnson warned this would be a “bloody and protracted” conflict that would be catastrophic for human life. Johnson maintained that the UK and US are prepared to impose extensive sanctions on Russia, including suspending Russian companies from trading in pounds and dollars. Johnson emphasized that NATO leaders learned from Putin’s annexation of Crimea and that Putin will “get more NATO” if he invades Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Government delivered a security assistance payload to Kyiv, Ukraine, on February 19. Ukraine’s defense minister stated that the shipment included unspecified rifles, machine guns, night vision and surveillance devices, and other military equipment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 19-20.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/19</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-19-ukraine-conflict-update-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/19" /><published>2022-02-19T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-19T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-19-ukraine-conflict-update-2.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 18-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian and Belarusian forces carried out the final day of active tactical exercises as part of the Joint Russian-Belarusian “Union Resolve 2022” exercise, scheduled to end on February 20. Russian forces currently remain scattered across several Belarusian training grounds and will likely require until at least February 20 to concentrate in southern Belarus if Russia intends to leverage them in an attack on Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin and Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko oversaw Russia’s “GROM” nuclear triad exercises, currently being held earlier in the year than previous annual iterations — likely to deter any significant NATO response to possible Russian aggression against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chairman of the Russian State Duma (Parliament) Vyacheslav Volodin announced the Duma will hold a session on February 22 to discuss and respond to what the Kremlin is calling a forced mass exodus of Russian citizens from the Luhansk and Donetsk People’s Republics (LNR and DNR).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Russian-backed Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics began the general mobilization of military-age male citizens amid increasingly frantic claims (amplified by Kremlin media) of an impending Ukrainian offensive against Donbas, including the publication of a faked Ukrainian offensive plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky notably left Ukraine to attend the Munich Security Conference in person, and urged Western states to take imminent action against Russian escalations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US and NATO officials emphasized unity and collective defense among member states against Russian escalations at the Munich Security Conference in Germany but announced no new policies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi stated Russia’s security concerns should be respected but urged all states to respect Ukraine’s sovereignty, marking a possible break in China’s previous full support for Russia in the current Ukraine crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin and Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko oversaw Russia’s ongoing “GROM” nuclear triad exercises from the Kremlin situation center on February 19 in a likely effort to deter NATO. The Kremlin typically conducts its annual GROM nuclear triad exercises in early fall and is likely holding them early to deter any NATO response to possible Russian offensive actions against Ukraine. Russian readouts did not specify the nature of Putin or Lukashenko’s roles in the GROM exercises beyond observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Air Force elements test-launched Kinzhal hypersonic missiles in unspecified locations. A Russian Northern Fleet submarine in the Barents Sea launched a strategic missile at the Kura Missile Testing Site in Kamchatka Krai. Additional Northern and Black Sea Fleet elements launched Kalibr cruise missiles and Zirkon hypersonic missiles at sea and air targets. Strategic Missile Force elements in the Kapustin Yar test site launched Iskander cruise missiles at unspecified targets. Likely Strategic Missile Force elements at the Plesetsk Cosmodrome in Arkhangelsk Oblast also launched Yars intercontinental missiles at targets in the Kura Missile Test Site, Kamchatka Krai. Unspecified Russian elements also launched cruise missiles from strategic missile carriers at targets in the Kura Missile Test Range in Kamchatka Krai and the Pemboi Missile Test Range in the Komi Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western Military District Commander Colonel-General Alexander Zhuravlev oversaw field training by the meteorological service of the WMD on February 19. Meteorologists prepared weather reports for aviation flights through the deployment of meteorological stations and mobile autonomous complexes. Servicemen used geostationary satellites to compile weather data and analyzed the hydrometeorological context of the area. This information was used to plan and execute flight exercises. It is unclear why the Russian Ministry of Defense separately reported on Zhuravlev’s attendance of a meteorological exercise. The Russian Ministry of Defense (MoD) last reported Zhuravlev attending exercises by the 1st Guards Tank Army in Moscow on February 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three hundred Russian 49th Combined Arms Army reconnaissance personnel and 60 vehicles conducted a tactical counter-reconnaissance exercise at the Kobu-Bashi Training Ground in Karachay-Cherkessia, Russia on February 19. The Russian reconnaissance units protected Russian units during combat and provided communications, information, and command and control support during the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unspecified Russian Southern Military District battalion tactical groups (BTGs) practiced new methods of long-range fire using tank and artillery units at the Prudboy Training Ground, Volgograd Oblast, Russia, on February 19. T-90A tanks and ATGM crews participated in the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 500 operators of the Black Sea Fleet coastal missile systems participated in an exercise to defend the Crimean Peninsula and Caucasian coast from mock missile strikes on February 19. Crews launched missiles at sea targets from designated positional areas and identified surface targets in Crimea and Krasnodar Krai. The exercise was part of a wider series of ongoing Russian naval exercises involving over 10,000 servicemembers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chairman of the Russian State Duma Vyacheslav Volodin announced on February 19 that the Duma will hold a session to discuss and respond to what the Kremlin is calling a forced mass exodus of Russian citizens from the Luhansk and Donetsk People’s Republics (LNR and DNR) on February 22. Duma member Viktor Vodolatsky claimed that nearly 36,000 people have arrived in Rostov from the LNR and DNR, 70 percent of whom volunteered to move. The LNR opened 61 checkpoints to facilitate the evacuation. Twenty-six Russian regions will receive refugees, including the Moscow region, Orlovsk, Tulsk, Kaliningrad, Yaroslav, Bryansk, Astrkhan, and South Ossetia. The Voronezh region was subsequently placed on high alert to accommodate refugee movements. In response to the alleged mass exodus, the United Russia party stated that they are providing support for the DNR and LNR in the form of charities, volunteer organizations, and legal aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian rhetoric on February 19 increasingly framed the situation as a manifestation of a Ukrainian genocide against Donbas, enabled by the West. Chairman of the State Duma Vyacheslav Volodin accused participants of the Munich Security Conference of ignoring what he claimed is an ongoing genocide against citizens of the Donbas region, and Russian Foreign Ministry spokesperson Maria Zakharova similarly claimed the West is blatantly overlooking ”crimes against humanity” in Donbas. Vice Speaker of Federation Council Konstantin Kosachev additionally accused the United States and its allies of encouraging a Ukrainian offensive against Donbas that is causing a mass exodus of Russian citizens and targets civilian infrastructure of the LNR and DNR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kremlin-sponsored media reported that Ukrainian paramilitary groups shelled Rostov Oblast on February 19, possibly to imply that Ukraine may use the Donbas crisis to attack Russia. Russian Police reported an initial explosion in the Mityakinskaya village in Tarasovsky District, Rostov Oblast. The Russian Federal Investigative Committee launched a criminal investigation into another multiple-launch-rocket-system shelling in Mityakinskaya, Rostov Oblast, that reportedly damaged two vacant residential buildings on February 19. The Committee also opened a criminal investigation after Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) Militia Head Denis Sinenkov’s car exploded on February 18. The DNR accused and detained reported Ukrainian agent Anton Matsanyuk for mining Sinekov’s vehicle. Russian media reported that Matsanyuk admitted to tracking the car and mining it with Ukrainian explosives. Russian media added that Matsanyuk organized a terrorist group to recruit Donetsk residents to carry out provocations in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov and French Foreign Minister Jean-Yves Le Drian discussed the conflict in Donbas during a phone call on February 19. Lavrov reiterated Kremlin claims that the Ukrainian government is hindering progress toward a peaceful solution by failing to abide by the Minsk II Accords, refusing to recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) as legitimate parties in the conflict, and refusing to grant the DNR and LNR special constitutional status within Ukraine. Lavrov accused Ukraine of building up military forces on the line of contact, militarizing the population, and inciting armed provocations in Donbas. Lavrov emphasized the need for international formats like the Normandy Format, of which France is a member, and the lack of acceptable alternatives to the Minsk agreements. Lavrov likely asked Le Drian to pressure Ukraine into engaging in international formats under Russian terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s delegation refused to attend a meeting of the Trilateral Contact Group to discuss de-escalating tensions in eastern Ukraine on February 19. The group’s chair, Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) representative Mikko Kinnunen, said that Russian representatives “linked their attendance to certain [unspecified] political preconditions.” The Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) and Luhansk People’s Republic (LNR) delegations also refused to participate in the Trilateral Contact Group meetings on February 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin issued Russia’s annual callup of military reservists for service in the Armed Forces, Rosgvardia, and state and federal security agencies on February 18 — earlier than the normal annual callup in March or April. The decree entered force immediately on February 18 but did not specify when reservists will enter training. The callup is not itself abnormal but has been issued earlier in the year than usual, with most callups issued in March or April. Russian reservists will likely support Russian militarization efforts and force posturing against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) claimed it obtained a Ukrainian plan for a five-day offensive to forcibly regain control of Donbas and push Russian-speaking populations to Russia on February 19. The DNR claimed that Ukrainian forces will strike in three stages, with the Ukrainian 30th Mechanized, 17th Tank, 95th Air Assault, and 26th Artillery Brigades attacking proxy positions from Kramatorsk and Debaltseve, Donetsk Oblast. The DNR added that Ukrainian forces will then advance from Alchevs’k, Luhansk Oblast, and Yenakijeve, Donetsk Oblast, up to the Russian border in three days. The DNR claimed that Ukrainian forces will also launch an offensive from Shyrokyne, Donetsk Oblast, and that Ukrainian sea troops advance from Novoazovs’k to Illovais’k and Ulyanivs’ke in Donetsk Oblast on February 21. The DNR added that Ukrainian forces on the Luhansk front will then move to Khrustalnyi, Luhansk Oblast. The DNR claimed that the Ukrainian 26th, 43rd, and 55th Artillery Brigades will conduct massive artillery, air, and drone strikes against civilian facilities, while establishing a blockade around Donetsk, Luhansk, Horlivka, and Alchevs’k. The DNR added that Ukraine and UK instructors have created misinformation videos featuring an actor playing a Russian defector who admits to chemical weapon terrorist attacks against Ukrainian targets to provide a pretext for Ukrainian invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Luhansk People’s Republic (LNR) is amplifying reports that Ukrainian forces are attempting to harm LNR and DNR evacuees, claiming that police safely disarmed a mined car under a bridge on an evacuation highway to Russia in Molodohvardiis’k, Luhansk Oblast. The LNR claimed Ukrainian sabotage and reconnaissance groups likely caused at least three gas pipeline explosions in Luhansk, resulting in several fires in the city. The LNR claimed that Ukrainian forces fired 120 mortars in Pervomais’k, Metalist, and Slov’yanoserbs’k, Luhansk Oblast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DNR claimed Ukrainian forces wounded an elderly civilian with shelling in Pikuzy, Donetsk Oblast. The DNR accused the Ukrainian 25th Brigade of shelling a water pumping station in Vasylivka, Donetsk Oblast, resulting in loss of electricity and the cessation of the station’s operation. The DNR issued another conflicting report that Ukraine’s 24th Separate Assault unit of the Right Sector damaged the Donetsk Filter Station. The DNR claimed that the inoperability of the station jeopardizes water supplies for over 40 settlements on both sides of the line of contact. The DNR also claimed to receive anonymous information about the mining of two hotels and four residential complexes in Donetsk, Donetsk Oblast. The DNR accused Ukrainian forces of disseminating leaflets among civilians to instigate panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LNR denounced media reports that proxy republics want to abandon the Minsk II Accords but restated proxy disinterest in scheduling any further Trilateral Contact Group meetings considering Kyiv’s provocations. The LNR added that the LNR and DNR will host a Trilateral Contact Group meeting if Ukraine sends specific proposals for final decisions on conflict settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (LNR and DNR) issued general mobilization decrees on February 19. The LNR decree called for a general mobilization of male citizens aged 18 to 55, claiming that the Ukrainian Armed Forces intensified their shelling and military buildup at the line of contact. The DNR similarly adopted a unanimous decree for general mobilization and announced that the DNR government would immediately shift its economy to a wartime footing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;belarusian-activity&quot;&gt;Belarusian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian and Belarusian forces carried out the final day of active tactical exercises as part of the Joint Russian-Belarusian “Union Resolve 2022” exercise, scheduled to end on February 20, at various training grounds across Belarus on February 19. Russian forces currently remain scattered across several Belarusian training grounds and will likely need until at least February 20 to concentrate in southern Belarus if Russia intends to leverage them in an attack on Ukraine. Belarusian Defense Minister Viktor Khrenin observed the day’s main exercises at Obuz-Lesnovsky (near Baranovichi in Western Belarus, 90 miles from the Ukrainian border), which included final joint tactical actions of the Belarusian Western Operational Command, the Russian Pacific Fleet Naval Infantry, and joint Belarusian-Russian aviation crews. The Belarusian MoD advertised that over 120 international media representatives attended exercises at Obuz-Lesnovsky in order to underline the Union State’s desire to be transparent and cooperative with the international media. Russian Naval Infantry from the Eastern Military District also practiced tactical airborne landings and helicopter reconnaissance at Obuz-Lesnovsky. The Belarusian MoD reported that Belarusian Signal Corps elements withdrew their forces and assets back to their points of permanent deployment after providing communications support during Union Resolve exercises. An unspecified Belarusian mechanized brigade participated in mock combat at the Gozkhy training ground (Western Belarus, about 175 miles north of the border with Ukraine). An unspecified Belarusian mechanized brigade worked with Russian marines to pursue a mock enemy and restore an advantageous border position at Baranovichi (Western Belarus, about 120 miles north of the Ukrainian border). Joint Belarusian-Russian special forces carried out anti-sabotage and reconnaissance measures at Maryina Gorka (Central Belarus, about 230 miles from the Ukrainian border).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several Russian units participated in exercises near the Ukrainian border, but the center of gravity of exercises remained in Western Belarus, and Russian units have not deployed to assembly areas in Belarus. Unspecified Belarusian special operations forces and Russian airborne and motorized rifle units practiced restoring combat capacity and conducted live-fire exercises at the Brestsky training ground (Southwestern Belarus, less than 30 miles from the Ukrainian border). Russian missile units carried out unspecified combat duties at Gomel (Southeastern Belarus, less than 30 miles north of the Ukrainian border). Belarusian missile forces carried out reconnaissance and combat in an area controlled by a mock enemy at Pinsk (Southern Belarus, about 40 miles from the Ukrainian border) and redeployed to a new combat area at Polessky (Southern Belarus, about 45 miles from the Ukrainian border).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ukrainian-activity&quot;&gt;Ukrainian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky urged Western states to take imminent action against the Russian military buildup at the Munich Security Conference (MSC) in Munich, Germany, on February 19. Zelensky called on Western countries to publicize the sanctions they plan to impose on Russia in the event of an escalation and urged countries to make no deals “behind Ukraine’s back.” Zelensky blamed western states for their “indifference” to the Russian military buildup at Ukraine’s border during his speech. Zelensky also invoked the 1994 Budapest Memorandum that granted security assurances for Ukraine‘s territorial integrity from Russia, the United States, and the United Kingdom in exchange for its denuclearization. Zelensky called for a meeting of the four signatory states and stated that a failure to hold such a meeting would put the entire package of measures “in doubt,” possibly insinuating a Ukrainian need to regain nuclear weapons. Zelensky also called on NATO to clarify Ukraine’s accession timeline. Additionally, Zelensky held bilateral meetings with UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson, German Chancellor Olaf Scholz, US Vice President Kamala Harris, and international financial institutions representatives during the visit. Separately, Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba participated in the G7 Foreign Ministers meeting at the Munich Security Conference on February 19. Kuleba said Ukraine and the United States would spare no diplomatic effort to protect Ukraine after meeting US State Secretary Antony Blinken. Kuleba also held a meeting with German Foreign Minister Annalena Burbock and French Foreign Minister Jean-Yves Le Drian to discuss Russia’s disinformation campaigns and the security situation in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ukrainian government provided several updates on February 19 on continued Russian proxy and propaganda activity to draw Ukraine into a military provocation, including the deployment of Wagner forces to Donbas. The Ukrainian Operational and Tactical Group East claimed on February 19 that Wagner Group operatives are in Donbas to conduct provocative offensives, mainly by detonating explosives in residential buildings. Defense officials including Defense Council Secretary Oleksiy Danilov, Ukrainian Defense Minister Oleksiy Reznikov, Deputy Minister for the Integration of Occupied Territories Iryna Vereschuk, and Ukrainian Armed Forces Commander-in-Chief Lieutenant General Yevhen Moisyuk visited the Donbas line of contact to further demonstrate Ukraine’s nonaggression, dedication to a political-diplomatic solution, and combat Russian propaganda efforts to portray Ukraine as the aggressor in Donbas. Ukraine’s State Security Service (SBU) said that proxy shelling and Russian propaganda efforts constitute a hybrid war against Ukraine and reiterated that Russian propaganda claims are fake and aim to destabilize Ukraine. The SBU reiterated that Ukraine will not give in to these provocations and that SBU officers remain on high alert against a possible Russian escalation. The Ukraine Defense Ministry also reported that Russian proxy forces in Pikuzy tried to pass off a proxy shelling as Ukrainian on February 19 to further promote Russian propaganda efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Vice President Kamala Harris and Secretary of State Antony Blinken met with several NATO and European leaders at the Munich Security Conference in Munich, Germany, on February 18-19. US Secretary of State Antony Blinken met with French Foreign Minister Jean-Yves Le Drian to discuss ongoing diplomacy with and deterrence against Russia on February 19. US Vice President Kamala Harris met with NATO Secretary General Jens Stoltenberg in Munich on February 18. Harris and Stoltenberg discussed reinforcements to NATO allies, including sending further US troops to Europe and providing $650 million in defense assistance to Ukraine. Harris also met with the leaders of Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia on February 18. Harris addressed the Munich Security Conference on February 19. Harris said that Russia is directly threatening European security in Ukraine with provocations and disinformation. Harris reaffirmed the US’ commitment to NATO’s Article 5 and the principles of sovereignty and territorial integrity. Harris said the US remains committed to diplomacy, but the US will impose financial sanctions and export controls on Russia and bolster NATO’s eastern flank in the event of an invasion. The US will also target “those who are complicit and those who aid and abet this unprovoked invasion.” Harris announced that the US recently deployed an additional 6,000 troops to Romania, Poland, and Germany, and put an additional 8,500 troops in the US on a heightened state of readiness. Harris concluded that NATO remains unified in the face of Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin visited Poland and Lithuania on February 18-19 to discuss defense cooperation, arms sales to Poland, and deterring Russian aggression. Austin held one-on-one meetings with Polish President Andrzej Duda and Polish Defense Minister Mariusz Blaszczak to discuss military cooperation and Russia’s military activities in and around Ukraine and Belarus in Warsaw, Poland, on February 18. Blaszczak thanked Austin for reinforcing NATO’s eastern flank by deploying additional US troops in Poland. Austin announced that the US Defense Department approved the sale of 250 M1A2 Abrams tanks to the Polish Armed Forces. Austin traveled to Vilnius, Lithuania to meet with Estonian Defense Minister Kalle Laanet, Latvian Defense Minister Artis Pabriks, and Lithuanian Foreign Minister Gabrielius Landsbergis to discuss Russia’s military buildup and Baltic requests for additional US force deployments to the region on February 19. Lithuanian President Gitanas Nauseda requested the US deploy additional troops to the region following the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Joe Biden discussed coordinated responses to the Ukraine crisis with transatlantic leaders by phone on February 18. Biden spoke with the leaders of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Poland, Romania, the UK, the European Commission, and NATO. Biden emphasized that the United States and its NATO allies are “in lockstep” and that the crisis has enhanced the “determination, unity, and resolve” of the European Union and NATO. Biden decried Russia’s disinformation campaign as an attempt to falsely justify aggression against Ukraine. Biden condemned the buildup of Russian troops around Ukraine’s borders and emphasized US and allied resolve to defend NATO territory and impose economic sanctions should Russia engage in aggressive action against Ukraine. Biden reiterated that NATO will not send troops to fight in Ukraine but reaffirmed their commitment to Ukrainian sovereignty and their support for the Ukrainian population. Biden said that Secretary of State Antony Blinken is scheduled to meet with Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov on February 24 at an unspecified location in Europe but warned that the door to diplomacy will close if Russia engages in military action before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Secretary of Defense Lloyd Austin said Russia could decide to attack Ukraine “in short order” on February 18. Austin said that Russia is prepared to “conduct a successful invasion.” Austin continued that this is likely not a bluff due to the mustering of combat aviation, medical support, and logistical support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-and-eu-activity&quot;&gt;NATO and EU Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO Secretary-General Jens Stoltenberg condemned Russia’s continued military buildup near Ukraine’s borders and discussed NATO’s diplomatic proposals to Russia at the Munich Security Conference in Munich, Germany, on February 19. Stoltenberg participated in a session at the Munich Security Conference alongside several other European leaders on February 19. Stoltenberg emphasized NATO’s readiness to engage in “substantive dialogue” with Moscow and called for Russia to withdraw its forces from Ukraine’s borders during his speech. Stoltenberg said he reiterated his offer to host new NATO-Russia Council meetings to Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov on February 17 and gave Lavrov several written proposals on increasing transparency of military activities and engaging on arms control. Stoltenberg also criticized China for the first time for joining Russia’s public calls to prevent NATO’s expansion at a time of rising “strategic competition” and reiterated the alliance’s unity to defend and protect all member states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European Union and NATO members emphasized their unity and resolve in opposing Russian aggression and supporting Ukraine during the Munich Security Conference in Munich, Germany, from February 18-19. Bilateral meetings between EU and NATO member states focused on the regional security implications of Russia’s military deployments to Belarus and Ukraine‘s border. European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen reaffirmed NATO and European opposition to Russia’s military buildup and called on Moscow to engage in dialogue to peacefully resolve the situation. Leyen and German Foreign Minister Annalena Baerbock emphasized Europe’s commitment to decreasing its dependency on Russian natural gas. Baerbock announced that Germany is prepared to pause the Nord Stream 2 project if Russia attacks Ukraine. European leaders stated the European Commission, the United States, the United Kingdom, and Canada have developed a robust package of economic sanctions to impose on Russia should Russia invade Ukraine and that an invasion would prompt political, economic, and strategic consequences. French and German Foreign Ministers Jean-Yves Le Drian and Annalena Baerbock condemned ceasefire violations in the Donbas and expressed concern about Russia staging incidents to create a pretext for military escalation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Group of Seven (G7) foreign ministers reaffirmed their commitment to Ukrainian sovereignty and condemned Russian aggression on February 19. The foreign ministers urged Russia to withdraw military forces from Ukraine’s borders, engage in diplomacy, and fulfill commitments to implement the Minsk Agreements in a joint statement. The G7 foreign ministers also threatened financial and economic sanctions against Russia if Russia pursues further military aggression against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia, France, and Germany issued warnings for citizens to avoid travel to Ukraine and for citizens in Ukraine to leave immediately due to escalating Russian military threats on February 19. NATO additionally relocated staff from Kyiv to offices in Lviv and Brussels on February 19. German Airline Lufthansa additionally announced on February 19 that it will suspend flights to Kyiv, Ukraine between February 21 and 28 but is maintaining flights to Lviv in Western Ukraine as of February 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government assessed on February 18 that Russia was involved in a February 15 and 16 cyberattack on Ukraine. Likely Russian hackers conducted a distributed denial of service (DDoS) cyberattack against the Ukrainian Defense Ministry (MoD), Ukrainian banks, and Ukrainian non-profit organizations on February 15. The UK stated that Russia’s Main Intelligence Directorate was involved in the DDoS attacks against Ukraine. The UK said the attack demonstrates Russia’s continued aggression and disregard for Ukrainian sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Foreign Secretary Liz Truss attended an Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) meeting on Ukraine and called for de-escalation and dialogue on February 18. Truss criticized Russia’s decision to not attend the OSCE meeting on Ukraine on February 18. Truss called on Russia to engage in dialogue and withdraw troops from Ukraine’s border. Ukraine previously requested the February 18 meeting with all participating OSCE states, citing ”unusual military activities” by Russia. The Kremlin claimed its drills were part of combat training plans and declined the invite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-international-activity&quot;&gt;Other International Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi said that implementing the 2015 Minsk II Agreement is the only way out of the Ukraine crisis and stated that all states’ sovereignty — including Ukraine’s — must be respected in a possible rebuke to Russia in a video address to the Munich Security Conference on February 19. Wang Yi stated that Russian concerns, including on eastward NATO expansion, should be heeded but that Ukraine should not be a frontline for conflict. Wang Yi added that Ukraine’s sovereignty and territorial integrity must be respected and protected under a multilateral system. Wang Yi criticized “certain major countries” for stoking confrontation by warning of an imminent invasion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 18-19.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine Conflict Update 2/18</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-18-ukraine-conflict-update-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine Conflict Update 2/18" /><published>2022-02-18T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-18T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/ukraine-conflict-update-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-18-ukraine-conflict-update-1.html">&lt;p&gt;This update covers events from February 17-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;military-events&quot;&gt;Military Events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian Ministry of Defense claimed that unspecified elements of the 1st Guards Tank Army of the Western Military District (WMD) began redeploying to permanent bases in Nizhny Novgorod after completing exercises on February 18. ISW has not seen evidence that any 1st Guards Tank Army elements have returned to their permanent bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Black Sea Fleet flagship Moskva conducted artillery exercises as part of ongoing Navy and Aerospace Forces exercises in the Black Sea on February 18. The Moskva repelled an air attack using its artillery systems and fired on various surface targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unspecified naval aviation crews of the Black Sea Fleet conducted aircraft withdrawal and deployment exercises as part of ongoing Russian Navy and Aerospace Forces exercises on February 18. Pilots of 10 Su-24 aircraft flew from Crimea to different operational airfields in unspecified locations in Russia. These aircraft may be redeploying to support operations against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-activity&quot;&gt;Russian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian Federation Council, Russia’s upper legislative chamber, will gather for an irregularly scheduled meeting on February 22; the Council has the power to permit Russian military interventions overseas. The meeting is reportedly to discuss pensions. However, the Federation Council has previously allowed for the use of Russian military forces in Syria. The Federation Council may vote to authorize an overt Russian military intervention in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kremlin spokesperson Dmitry Peskov announced on February 18 that Russian President Vladimir Putin will oversee Russia’s “Grom 2022” annual strategic nuclear triad exercises on February 19. Peskov added that Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko may also oversee the exercises if Putin decides to invite Lukashenko. Peskov said that Putin will observe the exercises from an unspecified “situational center” in Moscow, likely the Russian Ministry of Defense’s National Defense Control Center (NDCC). The Russian military conducting Grom nuclear readiness exercises in the winter is anomalous; the Russian military typically conducts annual Grom exercises in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Foreign Ministry spokesperson Maria Zakharova explicitly accused the Ukrainian government of conducting a genocide in Donbas in an interview with Kremlin-linked TV channel NTV on February 18. Zakharova also accused Western leaders of overlooking genocide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov said that Russia will not discuss Ukrainian security concerns separately from Russian security demands following talks with Greek Foreign Minister Nikos Dendias on February 18. Lavrov accused Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky of allowing external Western “management” to decide Ukrainian affairs. Lavrov said that there is no alternative to the Minsk II Accords and criticized Ukraine’s refusal to engage directly with the self-declared Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR). Lavrov falsely accused Ukraine of “grossly violating” its Minsk II Accords obligations by intensifying shelling against Donbas on February 17-18. Lavrov accused the Organization of Security and Cooperation in Europe Special Monitoring Mission in Ukraine (OSCE SMM) of “veiling” information about Ukrainian ceasefire violations and targeted attacks on civilians in Donbas. Lavrov claimed that an unspecified SMM report from “three years ago” (2018) found that the Ukrainian Armed Forces caused three times more destruction to civilian infrastructure than Russia’s DNR and LNR proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov criticized NATO states’ narratives about a Russian invasion in an interview with Kremlin media outlet RT on February 18. Lavrov accused NATO states of recruiting mercenaries from Kosovo, Albania, and Bosnia and Herzegovina to “throw Russia off balance” in Donbas. Lavrov claimed NATO previously fabricated a pretext to intervene, insinuating NATO may militarily intervene in Donbas. Lavrov reiterated that the Kremlin “will not be satisfied” with NATO’s current answer to Russian security demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Vladimir Putin presided over a Russian Security Council meeting about Ukraine, “growing tension provoked from outside,” and Russia’s security demands in Europe on February 18. The Kremlin readout provided no additional details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov and Belarusian Foreign Minister Vladimir Makei discussed “regional and international security” cooperation in the Union State and Russian security guarantees in Europe on February 18. Makei and Lavrov discussed unspecified “agreements” that Russian President Vladimir Putin and Belarusian President Lukashenko reached in Moscow on February 18. The Russian Foreign Ministry additionally stated that Lavrov and Makei discussed “Russian initiatives on ways to ensure sustainable legal security guarantees.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian State Duma Speaker Vyacheslav Volodin accused Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky of violating the Minsk II Accords by refusing to negotiate with representatives from the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics on February 18. Volodin added that Russia’s Investigative Committee opened a criminal investigation on the reports of civilian mass graves in Donetsk on February 16. Volodin said that leaders in Washington and Brussels have been silent on “Kyiv’s crimes” regarding the graves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian Deputy Foreign Minister Sergey Vershinin initiated a United Nations Security Council (UNSC) meeting about Ukraine and formally accused Ukraine’s government of “exterminating the civilian population” of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) on February 17. Vershinin told the UNSC that Ukraine has not implemented any of its commitments under the Minsk II Accords or under UNSC Resolution 2202 and that Russia had no obligations under and was not party to the Minsk II Accords. Vershinin also described DNR and LNR civilian experiences of alleged Ukrainian war crimes, sharing details from the Russian Investigative Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proxy-activity&quot;&gt;Proxy Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR) announced mass evacuations of civilians to Rostov Oblast, Russia, on February 18 ahead of a claimed Ukrainian offensive. The Kremlin preplanned and is coordinating this evacuation to support disinformation operations about Ukrainian plans to attack Donbas. DNR Head Denis Pushilin stated that Rostov Oblast government services will care for DNR residents upon their arrival. The DNR Ministry of Emergency Situations claimed that the DNR plans to evacuate 700,000 residents over an unspecified time period. Kremlin-sponsored media claimed that over 80 buses and an unspecified number of private vehicles arrived in Russia from Donbas as of February 18. Pushilin claimed that Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky will soon order an offensive against Donbas and use multiple launch rocket systems and Western-provided anti-tank and anti-aircraft weapons against civilians. LNR Head Leonid Pasechnik called on all residents that are not mobilized to evacuate to Russia “as soon as possible” and appealed to all men to “hold weapons to stand up for their land.” The LNR opened at least three checkpoints for evacuations on the LNR’s border with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin authorized a one-time payment of 10,000 rubles to every DNR and LNR refugee on February 18, likely to financially incentivize the migration necessary for the Kremlin’s information campaign. The Russian Ministry of Emergency Situations organized a refugee center and deployed an unspecified “operational group“ in Rostov Oblast on February 18. Officials in Rostov reportedly prepared hotels and children camps for refugees. The Russian Cabinet of Ministers also took measures to open border crossings between Donbas and Russia on February 18. Publicly available metadata showed that Pushilin and Pasechnik prerecorded their announcement videos calling for mass evacuations on February 16, before the DNR and LNR intensified shelling against Ukraine and falsely claimed that Ukraine shelled the DNR and LNR on February 17. Ukrainian Commander-in-Chief Valery Zaluzhny earlier stated that the DNR planned to conduct a mass evacuation on February 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) conducted a false flag car bomb attack against a car reportedly belonging to DNR Militia Chief Denis Sinekov and framed it as a Ukrainian attack on February 18. The DNR claimed that the attack occurred near a government building. Journalists affiliated with the Kremlin-linked ANNA News outlet recorded the destroyed car. The DNR also conducted checks of its emergency siren system throughout Donetsk on February 18 prior to the false flag attack to support an information operation claiming that Ukraine is preparing to conduct “massive shelling” against Donetsk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (LNR and LNR) rejected Kyiv’s offer to meet for a Trilateral Contact Group meeting on February 18. LNR and DNR officials said that a meeting with the Ukrainian government is meaningless because Ukraine does not have a real proposal and the meeting is part of a Ukrainian public-relations campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian media outlets amplified false claims by the Luhansk People’s Republic (LNR) about Ukrainian aggression against Donbas on February 17-18. The LNR claimed that Ukrainian special forces, not LNR militants, shelled a kindergarten in Stanytsa Luhanska on February 17. The LNR added that Ukrainian militants arrived at the kindergarten five minutes before film crews, emergency responders, and representatives from the Joint Center for Control and Coordination of the Ceasefire (JCCC). The LNR claimed that Ukraine violated the ceasefire 29 times on February 17 and conducted 20 instances of shelling in Katerinovka Molodezhnoye, Zolote, Geevka Slavyanoserbsk, Krymskoye-Sokolniki, Kalinkova, and Sanzharovka on February 18. The LNR also claimed that Ukraine has decided to conduct its main offensive in Svitlodarsk to cut off LNR defenses and transport lines. The LNR Internal Affairs Ministry announced that LNR law enforcement is increasing their patrolling, setting up additional checkpoints, and cracking down on curfew violators in response to LNR-claimed Ukrainian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ukrainian-activity&quot;&gt;Ukrainian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Defense Minister Oleksiy Reznikov stated that the intensified shelling campaign on February 16 and 17 by Russian proxies were “anomalous events” that significantly changed the security situation in Ukraine on February 18. Reznikov reiterated that the Ukrainian Ministry of Defense assesses that the probability of a “large-scale escalation” is low. Reznikov said that Ukraine’s main task at this time is to “curb this anomaly so that it does not become a prologue to escalation.” Reznikov stated that Ukrainian officials do not observe any Russian force withdrawals despite Russian claims. Reznikov stated that Ukraine’s Defense Ministry counts 149,000 Russian military personnel near Ukraine, including naval and air forces. Reznikov stated that Ukraine’s military attaché in Belarus will observe the main culminating events of the Union Resolve 2022 exercises in Belarus to lower tensions on February 19. Reznikov reiterated that Ukraine does not seek to use force to resolve the war in Donbas and appealed to Ukrainians living in occupied Donbas to not fear Ukraine. Reznikov restated development goals for the Ukrainian military, including elevating Ukraine’s military to NATO standards at the operational level, improving military logistics, increasing the size of Ukraine’s military to 100,000 personnel by 2025, abolishing conscription by 2024, raising defense spending to 3 percent of its GDP, increasing military salaries, and elongating servicemen’s contracts to at least 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ukrainian Ministry of Defense (MoD) stated that Russian proxies injured two civilians and two Ukrainian servicemen in Donbas on February 18. The MoD reported 33 instances of shelling in Chermalyk, Pishchane, Pivdenne, Shumy, Vodyane, Opytne, Hnutove, Nevel’s’ke, Svitlodars’k, Luhans’ke, Verkhn’otoretsk’ke, Mironivsk’kiy, and Niu-York in Donetsk Oblast and in Nyzhn’oteple and Troitske in Luhansk Oblast. Ukrainian Commander-in-Chief Valery Zaluzhny also reported that Russian proxies fired artillery at a United Nations (UN) humanitarian convoy of 12 vehicles in Schastia, Luhansk Oblast. The MoD stated that Kremlin-sponsored media outlets deliberately edited a video of their February 17 shelling of a kindergarten in Stanytsa Luhansnka, Luhansk Oblast, to present Ukrainian forces as the aggressor. The Ukrainian MoD said that Russian outlets changed their narrative from claiming that Kyiv staged a shelling against the kindergarten to openly accusing Ukrainian forces of actually firing at the kindergarten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine’s Main Military Intelligence Directorate (GUR) called on residents of Donetsk Oblast to not use public transportation and remain indoors due to bomb threats in occupied Donetsk on February 18. The GUR reported that Russian intelligence services are mining Donetsk civilian infrastructures to stage a provocation and further destabilize situation in Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Joint Forces Operation Commander Oleksandr Pavlyuk stated that the Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) fired 32 122 mm shells at a kindergarten and other structures in Stanytsia, Luhansk Oblast on February 17. Pavlyuk stated that Russian proxy forces shelled Ukrainian positions 49 times, 39 of which used artillery systems prohibited by the Minsk II Accords. Pavlyuk maintained that Russia and its proxies seek to commit atrocities against the people of Ukraine and that such violence is a part of a larger military and information campaign. Pavlyuk called on international media to document the atrocities committed by Russian and Russian-backed forces while denying Russian claims of “genocide.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba stated that Russian and Russian proxy allegations that Ukraine is preparing to conduct offensive actions against chemical production facilities in Donbas are disinformation on February 18. Kuleba reiterated Kyiv’s commitment to reaching a diplomatic — not military — solution to the war in Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian Defense Minister Oleksiy Reznikov discussed the growing threat of Russian military aggression against Ukraine at the NATO defense ministerial meeting in Brussels on February 18. Reznikov said that NATO officials discussed involving Ukraine in strengthening cybersecurity and jointly countering misinformation. Reznikov noted that several NATO defense ministers invited Ukraine and Georgia to join NATO summit in Madrid in June 2022. Reznikov also informed NATO about the proxy shelling of a kindergarten in Stanytsa Luhanska, Luhansk Oblast, on February 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine’s delegation to the United Nations asked the United Nations Security Council (UNSC) to discuss Russian proxy shelling of Stanitsa Luhanska and condemned Russia’s “hybrid war” against Ukraine on February 17. Ukraine’s delegation condemned the Russian Duma’s proposal to recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics as “tantamount to [Russia’s] deliberate withdrawal from the [Minsk II Accords].” The delegation called on Russia to take a “constructive stance” on making progress within existing agreements and warned that Russia would bear full responsibility for the collapse of the Minsk II Accords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky advocated for the creation of a “global [security] document” guaranteeing Ukraine’s security in an interview with RBK Ukraine on February 17. Zelensky called for the document to include security guarantees for Ukraine and to be implemented by “all world leaders.” He said that the objective of the document should be to support the financing, training, and rehabilitation of Ukraine’s armed forces. Zelensky reiterated that it is in the international community’s interest to strengthen Ukraine’s military because Ukraine protects Europe more broadly by deterring “any further [Russian] encroachment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-activity&quot;&gt;US Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Joe Biden said on February 18 that he is “convinced” that Russian President Vladimir Putin has decided to invade Ukraine in the “coming days” and will target Kyiv. He stated that Russia and Russian proxies in Donbas increased disinformation and likely “false flag” attacks to frame Ukraine as the aggressor. Biden emphasized that the United States and its allies will defend NATO territory and their collective security and will continue to support Ukraine with diplomatic and lethal aid. Biden called on Russia to keep diplomatic options open and warned that Russia will face economic sanctions and global outrage for escalating its aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United States Ambassador to the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Michael Carpenter stated that Russia increased its troop deployments from approximately 100,000 personnel as of January 30 to approximately 169,000 to 190,000 personnel as of February 18 despite publicly announcing troop withdrawals. This figure includes Russian forces deployed in Belarus and occupied Crimea. Carpenter stated that the US Government assesses that the Kremlin deployed amphibious assault landing ships of Russia’s Baltic Sea Fleet and Northern Sea Fleet to the Black Sea to augment Black Sea Fleet forces but did not specify that this deployment was in order to support an offensive. Carpenter noted that the Russian government continues to plan to fabricate pretexts to justify an invasion of Ukraine. Carpenter stated that Russia continues to conduct cyber operations against the Ukrainian defense and banking sectors. Carpenter accused Russia of violating the OSCE Vienna Document of 2011 for its unwillingness to credibly explain or properly notify European neighbors about Russia’s military buildups under the rubric of training exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin and Russian Defense Minister Sergei Shoigu discussed Russia’s military buildup near Ukraine on February 18. Austin called for “de-escalation, the return of Russian forces surrounding Ukraine to their home bases, and a diplomatic resolution.” TASS reported that the Russian Ministry of Defense said that the United States initiated the call to discuss “international security issues of mutual interest” without providing more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Policy reported on February 18 that four anonymous US intelligence officials stated that Russia is drafting a “kill list” targeting Ukrainian politicians and other prominent individuals in case of a Russian invasion of Ukraine. US intelligence sources said that Russia may either arrest or assassinate prominent political figures, anti-corruption activists, and Belarusian and Russian dissidents living in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Vice President Kamala Harris and NATO Secretary General Jens Stoltenberg emphasized US, NATO, and European commitments to opposing Russia’s military buildup at the Munich Security Conference on February 18. Harris emphasized NATO’s commitment to Ukrainian sovereignty and desire to engage in open dialogue with Russia. Harris stated that the US is committed to inflicting severe economic sanctions should Russia engage in aggressive action against Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United States Secretary of Defense Lloyd Austin and Polish Defense Minister Mariusz Blaszczak discussed US-Polish security cooperation in Warsaw on February 18. Austin commended Poland for serving as a model NATO ally and devoting 2 percent of its national budget to modernizing Poland’s military. Austin and Blaszczak reiterated that the entire NATO alliance stands in solidarity with Ukraine and will continue to work to overcome any challenge to peace and stability in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post reported on February 17 that Russia’s February 15 claim that it began withdrawing elements of the Western and Southern Military Districts was deliberate disinformation to hide additional deployments toward Ukraine’s borders. The Washington Post reported that four anonymous US officials said they had received “credible information that Russia’s claims may be part of a disinformation campaign designed to mislead” the United States. The Russian Defense Ministry released videos claiming to depict tanks and heavy equipment redeploying from areas near Ukraine after announcing force redeployments on February 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Secretary of State Antony Blinken stated on February 17 he plans to meet with Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov in an undetermined location in Europe next week (February 20 to 27) provided there is no further Russian invasion of Ukraine. Blinken stated that the US continues to track Russian efforts to fabricate claims to justify an invasion of Ukraine. The US Department of State reported that these claims may include terrorist bombings, discovery of mass graves, or chemical weapons attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Secretary of State Antony Blinken spoke with Polish Foreign Minister Zbigniew Rau on February 17. Blinken expressed support for Rau’s initiative to launch a Renewed European Security Dialogue at the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) to facilitate diplomacy with Russia. Blinken thanked Rau for Poland’s assistance with US citizens leaving Ukraine and reiterated his support for Ukraine’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US President Joe Biden and Italian Prime Minister Mario Draghi discussed ongoing diplomatic and deterrence efforts in response to Russia’s military escalation at the Ukrainian border on February 17. Biden and Draghi reiterated their commitment to Ukraine’s sovereignty and their readiness to impose severe economic costs against Russia if it further invades Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nato-activity&quot;&gt;NATO Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO Secretary General Jens Stoltenberg stated that NATO has not observed signs of any Russian force withdrawal or de-escalation during his opening remarks at a NATO defense ministerial meeting on February 17. Stoltenberg stated that NATO is devoted to continuing strong political and practical support for both Ukraine and Georgia. Stoltenberg stated that NATO will continue to work towards finding a diplomatic and political solution with Moscow. Ukrainian Defense Minister Oleksiy Reznikov participated in this ministerial and said that the NATO defense ministers praised Ukraine’s restraint and commitment towards political and diplomatic solutions. Stoltenberg welcomed European allies increasing their presence in NATO’s east and emphasized NATO’s unity in combatting Russia’s aggressive actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;individual-western-allies-activity&quot;&gt;Individual Western Allies’ Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German Foreign Minister Annalena Baerbock stated that Germany is prepared to pay a high economic price and suggested that the Nord Stream 2 pipeline will not materialize if Russia invades Ukraine during the Munich Security Conference on February 18. Baerbock stated that NATO is not going to negotiate over Ukraine’s head. The German government had refrained from explicitly mentioning targeting Nord Stream 2 as part of its sanctions against Russia for a renewed offensive against Ukraine prior to the Munich Security Conference on February 18. The Kremlin has not responded to Baerbock’s statement as of February 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia delivered an unspecified number of Javelin anti-tank systems to Kyiv, Ukraine, on February 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithuania’s Foreign Ministry called on Lithuanian citizens to leave Ukraine immediately on February 17. The ministry noted that the Russian military aggression may make it “impossible to leave the country.” The ministry also recommended Lithuanian citizens not travel to Belarus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Minister of State for Europe and North America James Cleverly gave a statement on Russia’s military build near Ukrainian borders at the United Nations Security Council on February 17. Cleverly reiterated UK support for the implementation of the Minsk II Accords and Ukrainian sovereignty. Cleverly condemned the Russian State Duma’s request that Russian President Vladimir Putin recognize the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics as independent and called on Russian authorities to reject that request. Cleverly called on Russia to engage in diplomatic processes to resolve the situation peacefully and “stand down” all its troops. Cleverly emphasized that if Russia chose to launch an attack, Russia would be met with “strength” and significant sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;belarusian-activity&quot;&gt;Belarusian Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin and Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko discussed unspecified joint responses to falsely claimed Western aggression on February 18. Lukashenko stated that Russia and Belarus are “on the verge of a conflict” with the West and need “to look for possible ways to repel a possible [Ukraine-based] attack.” Putin noted that both leaders will “collectively take all necessary measures to ensure the security of the two countries in light of the growing NATO military activity on the Union States’ external borders.” Putin stated that he and Lukashenko discussed the contents of his latest interactions with Western leaders and claimed that the US and NATO did not “adequately perceive” Russia’s security demands. Lukashenko stated that Belarus and Russia will continue to conduct joint military exercises and will respond to the West via military exercises or diplomatic channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin noted that both leaders may jointly preside over unspecified military exercises on February 19, which Kremlin spokesperson Dmitry Peskov later confirmed would be Russia’s strategic nuclear missile GROM exercises. Putin claimed that the “Union Resolve-2022” exercises did not “threaten anyone.” Putin additionally claimed that Ukraine systematically violates human rights in Donbas. Putin claimed that Kyiv will “restore civil peace in Ukraine and lift tensions” if it implements the Minsk II Accords and negotiates with representatives of the Donetsk and Luhansk People’s Republics (DNR and LNR). Putin accused Kyiv of sabotaging efforts to grant the DNR and LNR greater legal autonomy, grant amnesty to proxy fighters, and hold Ukrainian elections in the DNR and LNR. Lukashenko claimed that he and Putin have never discussed an invasion of Ukraine and accused the West of “frightening the whole world,” pushing Ukraine toward a provocation in Donbas, and conducting a hybrid war against Russia and Belarus. Putin said that the West will introduce sanctions against Russia and Belarus regardless of the situation in Ukraine to slow down Russian and Belarusian development. Putin warned that US allies will face economic consequences after imposing sanctions upon the Kremlin. Lukashenko also announced that Putin ordered the construction of a port in Leningrad Oblast to transport Belarusian fertilizers to help offset Western sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian and Belarusian forces continued the joint Russia-Belarus Union Resolve 2022 exercises at various training grounds in Belarus on February 18. The Belarusian Armed Forces practiced live-fire counterattacks under cover from air attacks carried out by a mock enemy at the Gozhsky Training Ground in Grodno, Belarus. Unspecified Belarusian special operations forces practiced landing measures and practiced destroying an enemy force at the Brest Training Ground. Russian Naval Infantry of the Eastern Military District worked alongside mechanized Belarusian units to hold a defensive line during a simulated battle at the Obuz-Lesnovsky Training Ground in Baranovichi, Belarus. Belarusian servicemen conducted counter-sabotage and counter-reconnaissance exercises in unspecified locations in the Gomel Oblast. Pantsir-S (surface to air missile) elements of the Russian Eastern Military District conducted electronic fires and covered troops in an air defense exercise in Luninets. Two Tu-22 strategic bombers of the Russian Aerospace Forces additionally patrolled Belarusian airspace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ISW Russia Team</name></author><summary type="html">This update covers events from February 17-18.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/YessZEx.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Russia-Ukraine Warning Update</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-18-russia-ukraine-warning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia-Ukraine Warning Update" /><published>2022-02-18T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-02-18T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/russia-ukraine-warning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-02-18-russia-ukraine-warning.html">&lt;p&gt;Russia may launch an attack on Ukraine on Saturday, February 19, 2022. The attack would likely begin with an air and missile campaign targeting much of Ukraine to decapitate the government and degrade the Ukrainian military as well as the ability of Ukrainian citizens to prepare to resist a subsequent Russian invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US and allied governments have been warning of such an attack for some days, pointing to the size of the Russian forces concentrated on Ukraine’s borders. Western officials have additionally said that Russian troops have moved to jumping-off positions for an invasion over the past 24 hours. The following additional conditions and indicators point to February 19 as an optimal date for a Russian attack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymir Zelensky will be in Germany at the Munich Security Conference. He is scheduled to speak at 1530 Munich time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His absence from Ukraine will degrade his ability to coordinate a response to any Russian attack and create more propitious circumstances for a Russian-sponsored attempt at a coup d’etat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian forces could close Ukrainian airspace to prevent Zelensky from returning to Kyiv.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Russian President Vladimir Putin will reportedly oversee Russian nuclear drills on Saturday, February 19, as well. Belarusian President Alexander Lukashenko will accompany Putin.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those drills are being conducted out of the usual exercise cycle and are clearly intended to deter any Western response to an attack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putin and Lukashenko will observe the exercises from an unspecified “situational center” in Moscow, likely the Russian Ministry of Defense’s National Defense Control Center (NDCC). That would put them in the best position to oversee conventional military operations as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Launching the attack during those drills would take maximal advantage of their deterrent effect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Russian proxy provocations in eastern Ukraine have increased dramatically since February 16, including an artillery barrage that damaged a kindergarten in unoccupied Ukraine and multiple other proxy attacks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian proxies have increased the frequency and drama of their claims of Ukrainian attacks on them as well as their false claims that Ukraine is preparing to invade occupied Donbas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russia’s proxies in Donbas began evacuating civilians to Russia ahead of a claimed Ukrainian offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian senior officials, including Putin, have been increasingly repeating and expanding on those claims this week.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The proxy campaign is likely intended on the one hand to draw Ukrainian forces into a response that Russia would then claim to be an attack and, on the other, to use false flag attacks and outright disinformation to fabricate justifications for a Russian attack to “defend” “Russian citizens” in occupied Donbas. This rhetorical and kinetic activity has crossed thresholds pointing to the likelihood of an actual Russian attack.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This update reflects a change to our assessments and forecasts. We have previously assessed that Putin was setting conditions to move Russian forces overtly into occupied Donbas and possibly conduct a limited invasion in unoccupied southeastern Ukraine and/or an air/missile campaign. We now assess that those Russian activities are extremely likely and imminent and that a much larger-scale Russian invasion is very possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Frederick W. Kagan and Mason Clark</name></author><summary type="html">Russia may launch an attack on Ukraine on Saturday, February 19, 2022. The attack would likely begin with an air and missile campaign targeting much of Ukraine to decapitate the government and degrade the Ukrainian military as well as the ability of Ukrainian citizens to prepare to resist a subsequent Russian invasion.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/zOZ0VAB.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/zOZ0VAB.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">香港181週年・開埠前史</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-01-26-hong-kong-181st-anniversary--pre-opening.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="香港181週年・開埠前史" /><published>2022-01-26T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-01-26T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hong-kong-181st-anniversary--pre-opening</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2022-01-26-hong-kong-181st-anniversary--pre-opening.html">&lt;p&gt;1841年，香港開埠，由此展開現代香港史。彼時，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;林肯 31歲……… 20年後，就任美國總統。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;維多利亞 21歲… 36年後，成為印度女皇。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;李鴻章 17歲…… 20年後，參與洋務運動。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;坂本龍馬 5歲 … 27年後，進入明治維新。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;三圖&quot;&gt;三圖&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;今，美利堅五洋治世 昔，不列顛七海通商&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1778年海圖&quot;&gt;1778年海圖&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/q7sqFXh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hong Kong in China Sea, 1778&quot; /&gt;
▲ Chart of the China Sea from the Island of Sanciam to Pedra Branca with the Course of the River Tigris from Canton to Macao, 1778. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-230807888/view&quot;&gt;🔍&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;開埠以前，駐華英商寄居（葡屬）澳門，通商（滿清）廣州。彼時，英商海圖亦以澳門爲節點。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1810年海圖&quot;&gt;1810年海圖&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/MBpLY5F.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hong Kong in China Sea, 1810&quot; /&gt;
▲ Chart of the Different Passages Leading to Macao Roads, 1810. &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b6/This_chart_of_the_different_passages_leading_to_Macao_Roads_LOC_88691655.jpg&quot;&gt;🔍&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1810年代，英國東印度公司勘探珠江口，詳細修正香港水域海圖。暗示香港業已成爲備選據點。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1839年6月，「虎門銷煙」，英商被逐；葡澳忌憚清廷不予保護。英商寄居商船，漂泊維港兩岸。顯示英商據點從澳門向香港轉移。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1841年測繪圖&quot;&gt;1841年測繪圖&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/VMCDEui.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hong Kong surveyed in 1841&quot; /&gt;
▲ Hong Kong Surveyed by Edward Belcher in HMS Sulphur, 1841. &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ee/Hong_Kong_Map_made_by_Edward_Belcher_in_1841.jpg&quot;&gt;🔍&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1841年1月25日，英艦「硫磺號」(HMS Sulphur) 測量船登陸香港島，後留「1841年版地圖」傳世。標誌英國完成佔據香港最後準備。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;三戰&quot;&gt;三戰&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;戰爭貿易 如影隨形&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;九龍海戰&quot;&gt;九龍海戰&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/rJrAqnH.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fort Victoria, 1841&quot; /&gt;
▲ 九龍炮台 (Fort Victoria), 1841.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1839年9月4日，「九龍海戰」於九龍對出海面爆發；當日晚近，以英方撤退告終。此戰拉開「第一次鴉片戰爭」序幕。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;事緣清廷6月「虎門銷煙」後，堅持封鎖貿易、驅逐英商，局勢在「貿易」與「戰爭」之間轉化。7月「林維喜案」產生外交糾紛，清廷施壓葡澳驅逐英僑，並封鎖其港九生活補給，觸發英方武力報復試探。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;官涌之戰&quot;&gt;官涌之戰&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bhJXqU8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kwun Chung Bay, 1860&quot; /&gt;
▲ 官涌 (Kwun Chung Bay), 1860.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1839年11月4日，「官涌之戰」於九龍半島官涌一帶對出海面爆發；經歷多輪海陸攻防戰；11月13日，以英方敗退告終。此戰促成英方增兵升級「第一次鴉片戰爭」。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;事緣英方決意武力打破清廷貿易禁運，局勢轉入「戰爭」區間。承日前虎門對出「第一次穿鼻之戰」，「官涌之戰」意奪維港北岸據點，圖破陸路封鎖。官涌油麻地一帶亦爲日後九龍開埠起點。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;虎門之戰&quot;&gt;虎門之戰&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/wXYO6uA.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storming of Chuenpi, 7 Jan. 1841&quot; /&gt;
▲ The Storming of the Forts and Intrenchments of Chuenpi, 1841.1.7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1841年1月7日，凱旋英軍於虎門外海集結軍力發動「虎門之戰」(Pearl River Campaign)；戰役經三道防線歷三個階段；2月27日，以英軍攻陷虎門要塞，獲勝告終。此戰導致「第一次鴉片戰爭」局面一邊倒向英方，亦奠定日後香港開埠政治條件與國際環境。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;戰役首日，「第二次穿鼻之戰」，英軍成功登陸，迫使議和。1月20日，雙方代表簽署《穿鼻草約》，包括「割讓香港」，惟未獲官方承認。自此，香港開埠箭在弦上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;三人&quot;&gt;三人&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;商戰殖民 三位一體&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;查理義律英商代表主導&quot;&gt;查理·義律（英商代表，主導）&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bYFi9dv.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles Elliot&quot; /&gt;
▲ Sir Charles Elliot (1801.8.15 – 1875.9.9), Chief Superintendent of British Trade in China (1836.12.14 - 1841.8.12), Administrator of Hong Kong (1841.1.26 - 1841.8.12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;開埠前夕，駐華商務總監查理·義律主導香港開埠全過程。1841年1月20日，簽署通報《穿鼻草約》，包括「割讓香港」。1841年1月26日，香港開埠，義律兼首任香港行政官。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;愛德華卑路乍殖民代表測繪&quot;&gt;愛德華·卑路乍（殖民代表，測繪）&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/GE9UTOO.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Edward Belcher&quot; /&gt;
▲ Sir Edward Belcher (1799.2.27 - 1877.3.18), Commander of HMS Sulphur (1840.12 - 1841.11, China).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;英艦「硫磺號」艦長愛德華·卑路乍代表英國首次測繪並登陸香港島。1841年1月24日，「硫磺號」獲委派經大嶼山西南駛往香港。1月25日上午8時15分，卑路乍率領官兵先行登陸港島北岸水坑口，並為女王三聲歡呼「Hip hip hooray」。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;戈登伯麥英軍代表主禮&quot;&gt;戈登·伯麥（英軍代表，主禮）&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/19GRUQx.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gordon Bremer&quot; /&gt;
▲ Sir Gordon Bremer (1786.9.26 - 1850.2.14), Commander-in-Chief of British Forces in the First Anglo-Chinese War (1839 - 1841, twice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「第一次鴉片戰爭」英軍總司令戈登·伯麥主禮香港開埠。1841年1月26日，英艦齊集，伯麥登陸主持升旗儀式，皇家海軍陸戰隊鳴槍，軍艦鳴炮。升旗禮日即開埠日。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>HOKO EYE</name></author><summary type="html">1841年，香港開埠，由此展開現代香港史。彼時， 林肯 31歲……… 20年後，就任美國總統。 維多利亞 21歲… 36年後，成為印度女皇。 李鴻章 17歲…… 20年後，參與洋務運動。 坂本龍馬 5歲 … 27年後，進入明治維新。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/VMCDEui.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/VMCDEui.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十八】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-25-hongkong-defense-war-1941--18.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十八】" /><published>2017-12-25T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-25T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--18</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-25-hongkong-defense-war-1941--18.html">&lt;p&gt;日軍為完善步砲協調及掃蕩守軍殘部，決定將總攻擊延至26日清晨開始。由於日軍大本營想盡早攻佔香港，以調派第38師團進攻瓜哇，日軍清晨再次勸降。12月25日上午6時，日軍派出被俘的退伍砲兵少校萬納思先（Major Manners）及淺水灣酒店市民委員會主席蕭士到對英軍處作非正式勸降。日軍保證早上7至9時停止軍事行動。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午9時，港島西南南朗山高射砲陣地被佔，香港仔東側屏障全失。正午時分，英軍總司令部開會後，總督楊慕琦以「香港尚能抵抗」回覆。日軍隨即派出軍機空襲，向守軍陣地發射300發重砲，並攻下巴理斯山，集結堅尼地道入口。英軍則在堅尼地道佈下地雷及路障，阻止前者前進。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午1時40分，守軍退至柯布連道及美利兵房建立陣地。下午2時30分後，灣仔峽失陷，馬己仙峽守軍苦戰。下午2時50分，米杜息士營營長指柯布連道防線受九龍及正面砲火交叉打擊，只能維持多半小時。下午3時，壽臣山守軍在包圍下投降，小香港彈藥庫落入日軍手中。此時，西旅只有6門榴彈砲，每砲只剩60發砲彈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午3時15分，駐港英軍司令莫德庇向楊慕琦報告：左翼方面，禮頓山、海軍醫院失守，柯布連道難以維持，海軍船塢只能抵抗多兩小時。中部方面，灣仔峽及馬己仙峽已經失陷。右翼方面，班納山及壽臣山失守，最後的彈藥庫已落入敵軍手中。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;莫德庇估計，日軍最快於下午6時攻入維多利亞城，屆時位於域多利兵房亦將陷入近戰，癱瘓指揮系統，故此應該盡快投降，以免其他部隊未收到指示而繼續抵抗，因而被殘害。楊慕琦立即知會布政司及律政司，致電駐港海軍最高級的軍官，三人均贊成投降。楊慕琦即向倫敦發電文，準備相應行動。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午4時半起，守軍陣地開始舉起白旗。莫德庇派人員到東角向日軍交代即時停戰及投降，日軍要求楊、莫兩人下令英軍停火，前往日軍指揮部。 傍晚時分，兩人抵達半島酒店，向第23軍司令酒井隆中將投降。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;東旅方面，旅長華里士根據莫德庇凌晨「hold on to the last」的電令，繼續抵抗。根據日軍紀錄，第230聯隊第2中隊靠近聖士提反書院主樓時，深恐其為防禦據點，如臨大敵，不知其為英軍醫院。凌晨4時，屢屢受創的第2中隊進入院內大肆屠殺，最少60人被害，包括56名負傷臥床的英軍及加拿大軍人，部分醫護及學校職工都被刺刀殺死。英軍早上曾嘗試反攻，但被擊退。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上8時，華里士不相信英軍軍使傳來的投降消息，直至26日凌晨1時30分，華里士副官攜同米杜息士營營長簽署的手令回來，他才信服，但已不及下令摧毀赤柱砲台。凌晨2時30分，華里士下令東旅停火投降，成為最後投降的部隊。香港主要戰事至此告終。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;陳策突圍&quot;&gt;陳策突圍&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;當日晚上，中國國民黨駐港代表陳策聯同十多名英國高級軍官，及三十多名其他官兵及情報人員，乘魚雷艇突破日軍海上封鎖，最終抵達惠州，成功逃出日佔區。其後，英國官兵經雲南、緬甸、到達印度及英倫。為表揚陳策貢獻，英皇授予他大英帝國爵級司令勳章（KBE）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/24/174328/VJMedia-2017-12-24-%E4%B8%8A%E5%8D%886.00.17.png&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt;
▲ 陳策及部份英軍到達惠州留影。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">日軍為完善步砲協調及掃蕩守軍殘部，決定將總攻擊延至26日清晨開始。由於日軍大本營想盡早攻佔香港，以調派第38師團進攻瓜哇，日軍清晨再次勸降。12月25日上午6時，日軍派出被俘的退伍砲兵少校萬納思先（Major Manners）及淺水灣酒店市民委員會主席蕭士到對英軍處作非正式勸降。日軍保證早上7至9時停止軍事行動。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/24/174328/201712_Onthisday_18-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/24/174328/201712_Onthisday_18-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十七】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-24-hongkong-defense-war-1941--17.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十七】" /><published>2017-12-24T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-24T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--17</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-24-hongkong-defense-war-1941--17.html">&lt;p&gt;凌晨時份，雙方在灣仔峽及金馬倫山交戰。早上8時30分，日軍第230聯隊決定於正午沿灣仔峽推進、再襲向禮頓山。禮頓山上的米杜息士營殘部一直堅守至西旅准許撤退為止，才於向西突圍。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午6時20分，日軍展開對位處香港仔東北之斑納山的攻勢，由大隊砲及獨立山砲隊砲轟，盡毀摩利臣山上7座機槍陣地。 晚上，肉搏攻擊班為主力，以手榴彈、炸藥及擲彈桶陸續攻佔守軍陣地。翌日凌晨2時，日軍迫退港島西南班納山的守軍，佔領山頭。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上10時，守軍懷疑日軍正向巴里士山的防空洞網絡及馬己仙峽推進，進入灣仔市區。隨著日軍步步進逼，西旅需要冒險派出車隊闖進已落入日軍範圍小香港彈藥庫，才得以補充彈藥。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;赤柱戰線方面，東旅在日軍砲擊下緩緩後撤。晚上8時30分，日軍沿赤柱灘道南進，部隊由3輛九四式輕裝甲車領頭。英軍防線則由香港防衛軍第1、2連及米杜息士營D連防守，由防衛軍第2連連長科沙福少校指揮，附近有第965防衛砲連的2門2磅速射砲協防。日軍接近守軍陣地時，科沙福下令發射照明彈照常日軍隊列，迅速擊破3輛裝甲車，令後者陷入混亂。經歷激烈駁火，該防衛砲連最後只有3名砲手生還。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;平安夜晚上11時，楊慕琦及莫德庇分別向守軍發出聖誕賀詞：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“From H.E. to Troops:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In pride and admiration I send my greetings this Xmas day to all who are fighting and to all who are working so nobly and so well to sustain Hong Kong against the assault of the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fight on, Hold fast for King and Empire. God bless you all in this your finest hour”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“From Fortress HQ to Tps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Xmas greetings to you all. Let this day be historical in the proud annals of our Empire. The order of the day is Hold Fast”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;是晚，日軍為崩解守軍抵抗意志，徹夜砲轟維多利亞城，包括中區堅尼地道、海軍船塢、域多利兵房及總司令部等地。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">凌晨時份，雙方在灣仔峽及金馬倫山交戰。早上8時30分，日軍第230聯隊決定於正午沿灣仔峽推進、再襲向禮頓山。禮頓山上的米杜息士營殘部一直堅守至西旅准許撤退為止，才於向西突圍。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/23/174288/201712_Onthisday_17-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/23/174288/201712_Onthisday_17-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十六】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-23-hongkong-defense-war-1941--16.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十六】" /><published>2017-12-23T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-23T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--16</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-23-hongkong-defense-war-1941--16.html">&lt;p&gt;凌晨1時20分，香港工務局向總司令部警告：港島供水瀕臨癱瘓，全依賴薄扶林水塘的供應，直言市區已經無望（The Town is now helpless）。其實，九龍新界淪陷，同時意味喪失總水塘容量之六成。失去大潭水塘後，供水能力只剩開戰前的一至兩成。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;凌晨時份，日軍第228聯隊攻佔金馬倫山，加軍倉皇撤出，附近英軍則堅守歌賦山及灣仔峽。上午8至9時，英軍不斷派出搜索隊前往金馬倫山，偵察軍情，無意中阻礙日軍進攻。對照第228聯隊紀錄，聯隊佔領山頭後的上午面對守軍7次「進攻」，官兵被迫不眠不休。赤柱砲台亦奉命砲擊支援，導致碎石崩塌，妨礙日軍前進。上午約8時，日軍大舉進攻銅鑼灣及禮頓山一帶。上午11時30分，英軍退至波斯富街一帶，少量士兵仍守在山上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;黃泥涌峽方面，第230聯隊突擊守軍於聶高信山北部的防線。正午12時，日軍攻佔聖亞伯特女修院（今玫瑰崗學校）東面山地，擊散灣仔峽以北的英軍。隨著日軍步步進迫，守軍唯一未被攻佔的彈藥庫「小香港」及南朗山高射砲台漸漸被孤立（日軍已於21日起投入虜獲的英軍榴彈砲，以求盡快突破防線）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;東旅方面，日軍已將第229及230聯隊的第1大隊，合併成「赤柱攻略隊」，備有山砲兵中隊，專責對付東旅。上午7時30分，英軍一度反攻，但遭猛烈還擊。加拿大皇家來福槍營營長荷姆（William J. Home）認為不斷反攻只會徒增傷亡，與旅長華里士產生分歧，爭論不已。下午7時，東旅向赤柱半島收縮，前線沿馬利諾修道院佈防。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;義犬甘德中士&quot;&gt;義犬甘德中士&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;甘德（Gander，另譯作根達）是一頭紐芬蘭犬，原名叫Pal，曾經抓傷小孩，差點要人道毀滅。後來，軍人Fred收養牠，改名為Gander，成為加拿大皇家來福槍營的吉祥物。後來，甘德「晉升」為中士，並且隨團來港。甘德後來於槍戰中為保護加拿大士兵，一口把日軍投擲的手榴彈帶到遠處，爆炸身亡。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2000年，甘德獲英國政府頒發表揚動物戰時貢獻的Dickin Medal（相當於動物界的維多利亞十字勛章）。2013年，曾在香港作戰並被日軍俘虜四年的加軍士官長（Sergeant Major）George MacDonell 出版”A Dog Named Gander”一書，以作紀念。2015年12月6日，加拿大二戰悼念儀式中，嘉賓隊伍由一頭紐芬蘭犬領頭進場，場刊更作出專題介紹。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">凌晨1時20分，香港工務局向總司令部警告：港島供水瀕臨癱瘓，全依賴薄扶林水塘的供應，直言市區已經無望（The Town is now helpless）。其實，九龍新界淪陷，同時意味喪失總水塘容量之六成。失去大潭水塘後，供水能力只剩開戰前的一至兩成。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/22/174217/201712_Onthisday_16.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/22/174217/201712_Onthisday_16.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十五】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-22-hongkong-defense-war-1941--15.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十五】" /><published>2017-12-22T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-22T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--15</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-22-hongkong-defense-war-1941--15.html">&lt;p&gt;經歷連日激戰，日軍漸漸在港島站穩陣腳，但進度落後於原定計劃，黃泥涌峽西端守軍的縱深陣地仍然健在，而赤柱砲台及高射砲陣地無損。受著陸軍省的壓力，軍司令部派參謀到師團部督戰，師團部再派參謀到各指揮部協調，並往前線了解戰況。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午1時，日軍第230聯隊進攻溫尼柏營D連連部。加軍彈藥耗盡，軍官全數陣亡，遂於上午4時30分投降，部份士兵潛回所部繼續作戰。隨後，第230聯隊轉向跑馬地和灣仔進發。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午10時，第229聯隊第10中隊佔領淺水灣71號「灣上別墅」及附近，切斷淺水灣道東西旅陸上交通，分割守軍東西兩旅。上午10時30分，英軍總司令部下令東旅指揮所有赤柱半島的部隊，華里士即部署縱深防禦。至此，東旅只剩下少量火砲砲彈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午11時30分，金馬倫山的溫尼柏營及司徒拔道的蘇格蘭營同遭砲擊及空襲。中午時分，第229聯隊攻佔赤柱半島北面的老虎山，來福槍營C連撤退後回頭反攻，於傍晚重奪山頭。早前已被日軍佔領的大潭水塘抽水站鍋爐由於燃料耗盡而熄火，影響港島大部份地區供水。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午2時，淺水灣酒店食水斷絕。莫德庇及華里士同意市民委員會建議，英兵於晚上10時撤出酒店，留下平民向日軍投降。臨近凌晨，第229聯隊第3大隊進軍至酒店，接受住客投降，雖未報復市民，但屠殺在「余堡」俘虜的加兵及英軍後勤人員。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">經歷連日激戰，日軍漸漸在港島站穩陣腳，但進度落後於原定計劃，黃泥涌峽西端守軍的縱深陣地仍然健在，而赤柱砲台及高射砲陣地無損。受著陸軍省的壓力，軍司令部派參謀到師團部督戰，師團部再派參謀到各指揮部協調，並往前線了解戰況。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/21/174172/201712_Onthisday_15-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/21/174172/201712_Onthisday_15-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十四】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-21-hongkong-defense-war-1941--14.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十四】" /><published>2017-12-21T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-21T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--14</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-21-hongkong-defense-war-1941--14.html">&lt;p&gt;凌晨時份，英軍組織反攻黃泥涌峽。上午7時，西旅溫尼柏營B、C連分別由中峽南部及北部進攻，夾擊日軍第228聯隊。隨後兩小時，兩連反覆突擊，殲滅兩個日軍小隊，可惜寡不敵眾，終被擊退。此役中，B連全數軍官陣亡、7名士官及29名士兵戰死。上午8時，旁遮普營A連自南攻上壽臣山，雙方爆發激戰，營長陣亡，只有八人生還。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午7時，東旅發動進攻。英日兩軍在蓮花井山及龜山一帶交火。下午2時，加軍來福槍營及香港防衛軍搶先登上蓮花井山山頂，向推進中的第229聯隊第1大隊第2中隊掃射，殺死中隊長在內36人，其餘日兵重傷。東旅雖然完成第一階段目標，但是部隊已見疲憊。日軍增援其後到達大潭，英軍發現其偵察部隊配備九四式輕裝甲車。英軍缺乏各戰車裝備而無法突破，遂於下午6時撤退。東西旅反攻，均失敗告終。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;海空兩軍方面，雖然日本海軍第二遺支艦隊依然被英軍海岸砲台牽制，無法靠近，但成功空襲活躍多時的老式蟬號砲艦，後者隨後於東博寮海峽沉沒。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午，莫德庇向總督楊慕琦表示戰敗在即，後者向倫敦發電文，請求投降條件，以免戰火波及人口稠密的維多利亞城，造成更多傷亡。倫敦時間下午3時30分（香港時間晚上11時30分），英國政府經開會討論後向香港發電文，命令香港總司令及總督抵抗至最後（resist to the end）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;英皇喬治六世、陸軍部長先後向香港發電，鼓勵守軍堅持下去。接下來，英軍不再反攻，死守陣地。為免重要物資落入日軍手中，殘餘的砲台奉命砲擊九龍半島的油庫及倉庫。這場註定不會勝出的戰役，走到結局只是時間的問題。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">凌晨時份，英軍組織反攻黃泥涌峽。上午7時，西旅溫尼柏營B、C連分別由中峽南部及北部進攻，夾擊日軍第228聯隊。隨後兩小時，兩連反覆突擊，殲滅兩個日軍小隊，可惜寡不敵眾，終被擊退。此役中，B連全數軍官陣亡、7名士官及29名士兵戰死。上午8時，旁遮普營A連自南攻上壽臣山，雙方爆發激戰，營長陣亡，只有八人生還。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/20/174125/201712_Onthisday_14.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/20/174125/201712_Onthisday_14.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十三】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-20-hongkong-defense-war-1941--13.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十三】" /><published>2017-12-20T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-20T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--13</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-20-hongkong-defense-war-1941--13.html">&lt;p&gt;早上4時，日軍第229聯隊因地形所限及屢被射擊而偏離原定路線，南下到達淺水灣酒店附近集合，但不少部隊迷路走失。當時，酒店有200名住客及46名英軍。早上7時40分，30名日軍進入酒店，遭英軍突襲而逃進車庫。守軍送婦孺至底層，組織防禦。早上10時，援軍抵達，與守軍突襲車庫日軍（包括17名大隊指揮人員），後者燒燬密碼書及通訊器材倉皇脫出。英軍嘗試追擊，但被擊退，唯有返回酒店及「余堡」大宅。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午9時30分，日軍第二遣支艦隊派出雷號及電號驅逐艦靠近東部海域。兩艦進入赤柱砲台20公里範圍時，砲台三門9.2吋砲（射程達26.7公里）齊射，彈落雷號兩側。第二輪齊射在雷號舷側10米落下，令雷號船體輕微損毀。日軍估計第四次齊射將擊中艦隻，便施放煙幕調頭駛離，守軍海防砲成功阻嚇日艦進侵。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;正午時分，第38師團長佐野忠義中將在守軍砲火下把指揮部由九龍城遷至北角寶馬角，以掌握日軍實際進展。下午1時35分，莫德庇下令反攻，指示西旅在下午3時30分東進，清剿黃泥涌峽內的敵人。下午2時，行進中的英軍遇上往西攻佔大坑的日軍第229聯隊，唯有轉攻為守。黃泥涌峽西邊的皇家蘇格蘭營面對日軍4個新投入前線的大隊，只能繼續維持對峙局面。另一方面，東旅部隊曾經一度突入黃泥涌峽，但再被擊退。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午4時，第228聯隊因大霧提早進攻聶高信山，擊退蘇格營D連側翼。晚上8時，聯隊大致控制聶高信山， 東西旅間的空隙日益擴大，通訊全繫於南端淺水灣的薄弱陣線。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/19/174085/b56ff9f5-s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt;
▲ 雷號驅逐艦，攝於1933年，出自MONOCHROME SPECTER。吹雪型驅逐艦以電焊等投術輕量化艦體，以搭載重型武裝同時維持速度。曉型（III）型為吹雪型的後期改進版，擴大了艦橋，改良了引擎以提升航行性能及加長續航距離。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">早上4時，日軍第229聯隊因地形所限及屢被射擊而偏離原定路線，南下到達淺水灣酒店附近集合，但不少部隊迷路走失。當時，酒店有200名住客及46名英軍。早上7時40分，30名日軍進入酒店，遭英軍突襲而逃進車庫。守軍送婦孺至底層，組織防禦。早上10時，援軍抵達，與守軍突襲車庫日軍（包括17名大隊指揮人員），後者燒燬密碼書及通訊器材倉皇脫出。英軍嘗試追擊，但被擊退，唯有返回酒店及「余堡」大宅。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/19/174085/201712_Onthisday_13.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/19/174085/201712_Onthisday_13.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十二】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-19-hongkong-defense-war-1941--12.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十二】" /><published>2017-12-19T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-19T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--12</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-19-hongkong-defense-war-1941--12.html">&lt;p&gt;隨著港島東北岸防線逐漸瓦解，西旅旅長羅遜准將調兵於渣甸山及禮頓山一帶建立防線，待日出後反攻。日軍第230聯隊本應向西進攻大坑，但聯隊隊長東海林俊成判斷英軍集結渣甸山而改向南推進。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;由於行軍正值守軍轉換日夜間陣地的時段，聯隊在未被發現下沿金督馳馬徑誤闖黃泥涌峽守軍正中央，與西旅指揮部只有一街之隔，處於守軍零散陣地之間。與此同時，第229、228聯隊在混亂中從畢拿山、柏架山及大潭水塘東北，西襲黃泥涌峽。三聯隊動在誤打誤撞下，劍指防守薄弱的西旅指揮部。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;早上5時，英軍發現日軍合圍，展開攻擊。日軍最初受著多方面夾攻，承受重大傷亡，但憑藉數量及速射砲火力優勢，戰況逆轉。皇家蘇格蘭營及溫尼柏營主力，由於早前被調走，未能及時回防西旅指揮部。早上6時30分，皇家工兵到達黃泥涌峽，但受日軍阻擋，無法接近西旅指揮部。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;羅遜突圍戰死反攻鍛羽而還&quot;&gt;羅遜突圍戰死　反攻鍛羽而還&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午7時，第230聯隊由南向北攻擊指揮部。上午8時，第230聯隊佔領赤柱峽，消滅該地所有守軍砲兵，封鎖黃泥涌峽南北出口。上午10時，羅遜與莫德庇通話，曰「I am going outside to fight it out」，即破壞指揮部通訊設施，率領指揮人員突圍戰鬥到底。可惜，他們甫離開即被包圍的日軍掃射，幾近悉數陣亡。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;中午時分，皇家蘇格蘭營A連在砲火下奮勇前進，終於到達西旅指揮部外圍，但三名排長、連士官長戰死，只剩下15人能夠戰鬥（滿額的步槍連約100人）。皇家海軍步兵部隊於增援途中亦遭伏擊，殘部退至淺水灣大宅抗戰至晚上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午1時，莫德庇發出「第6號作戰指令」，指示西旅全面東進，趕日軍至岸邊。由於莫德庇未能掌握最新情報，指令低估日軍數量，未知北角曉士兵團幾近被殲，東旅則在拉吉普營潰散後往赤柱半島收縮。反攻於下午3時開始，但旋即陷入膠著。東旅兩次突入黃泥涌峽警署的嘗試均告失敗，傷亡慘重，被迫撤後。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;奧士本捨己救人港大生頑抗到底&quot;&gt;奧士本捨己救人　港大生頑抗到底&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;渣甸山方面，戰況同激烈。加拿大溫尼柏營D連被擊潰後，A連殘部在連士官長奧士本帶領下與第228聯隊且走且戰，奧士本逐一將手榴彈拋回敵軍。其間，有一枚落於墼壕，奧斯本警告同袍後縱身覆蓋手榴彈，捨己救人。渣甸山防衛軍駐守的機槍堡亦不斷被攻擊，港大文學院學生洪棨釗下士一度暫代指揮，其後突圍時被射死。傍晚時份，守軍終無力對抗，渣甸山宣告失陷。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;至此，黃泥涌峽成為無人地帶，日軍控制其東、南、北邊。英軍據有西邊，散部固守附近各處。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/18/173997/201712_Onthisday_12_extra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt;
▲ 1941年10月，羅遜准將及其幕僚前往香港途中。圖中4位只有右一的布殊上尉在香港保衛戰中生還。&lt;br /&gt;
左一：林登少校，因總部電話線路被破壞，於12月21日嘗試穿越日軍防線至灣仔總部傳遞信息，陣亡。&lt;br /&gt;
左二：羅遜准將，加拿大陸軍訓練總監，是加軍在二戰中軍階最高的陣亡軍官。日軍欣賞其果敢表現，給予葬禮。&lt;br /&gt;
左三：軒尼詩上校，與羅遜准將一同於12月19日離開西旅指揮部突圍，同被日軍機關槍掃射殺死。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">隨著港島東北岸防線逐漸瓦解，西旅旅長羅遜准將調兵於渣甸山及禮頓山一帶建立防線，待日出後反攻。日軍第230聯隊本應向西進攻大坑，但聯隊隊長東海林俊成判斷英軍集結渣甸山而改向南推進。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/18/173997/201712_Onthisday_12v2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/18/173997/201712_Onthisday_12v2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十一】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-18-hongkong-defense-war-1941--11.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十一】" /><published>2017-12-18T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-18T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--11</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-18-hongkong-defense-war-1941--11.html">&lt;p&gt;早上7時30分，日軍砲兵隊砲擊太古及筲箕灣，同時空襲港督府及摩星嶺砲台。北角油庫被砲彈誤中起火，連同寶馬角的大火，濃煙隨東北風飄，形成煙幕，影響守軍視野。下午6時，筲箕灣橡膠廠及寶馬角油漆廠因砲擊起火，煙霧更濃。銅鑼灣英皇道因砲擊而滿佈車輛殘骸，北岸交通隨後完全癱瘓。 如今守備港島東北的印度拉吉普營多次被切斷通訊，大量探射燈失靈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;傍晚6時半，日軍發動登陸前掩護砲擊，目標是登陸地點一帶的守軍設施及陣地。晚上7時，日軍開始登艦。7時10分，日軍砲擊目標轉為內陸地區。7時20分，日軍啟航出發。同時，太古船塢被擊中起火。日軍預定的登陸地點，均被大火照亮，有利搶灘。駐守的拉吉普營命令各機槍堡及陣地向接近岸邊的日軍開火，但不足以擊退敵軍。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上8時15分至28分，在砲火彈幕有序掩護下，日軍第230聯隊、第228聯隊及第229聯隊由西至東，先後於北角、太古及愛秩序灣登陸。目睹三發象徵成功登陸的紅色照明彈在黑夜輝映後，第23軍司令酒井隆中將與第38師團長佐野忠義中將在司令部舉杯祝酒。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在缺乏中央指揮下，拉吉普營各連頑抗日軍。第230聯隊受到在北角發電廠的D連及曉士兵團的抵抗而無法進入英皇道。第228聯隊第2大隊與與C連在太古船塢進行白刃戰。第229聯隊第3大隊擊潰了早就需要休整的A連。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/17/173970/201712_Onthisday_11_extra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt;
▲ 日軍第10獨立山砲聯隊以四一式山砲（明治41年（1911年）開始量產，為聯隊火力支援裝備）砲轟北角，煙囪為北角發電廠。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;約1小時後，日軍第二波部隊登陸，拉吉普營繼續對抗數量6倍於己的敵軍。東旅旅長華里士知悉日軍登陸後，下令集中猛轟東北岸。在印軍猛烈砲火下，日軍三個聯隊未能按照原訂計劃如旋轉門般順時針方向推進，各自向東、南、西方盲進。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;西旅旅長羅遜除派遺米杜息士營（1st Bn., The Middlesex Regiment，1881年成立，因其先驅第57步兵團指揮官在1811年半島戰爭中，屢被法軍槍傷仍然下令軍團死戰而被稱為”Die-hards”；屬裝備火力較強的機關槍營，1937年來港）第16排增援北角，亦下令「機動縱隊」佔據向西俯轍黃泥涌峽、向南遙指淺水灣的渣甸山及山脊地段。午夜時份，拉吉普營終告不支，羅遜命其營部後撤至大風拗附近。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;曉士兵團簡介&quot;&gt;曉士兵團簡介&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;兵團由一群年過55歳英藉商人及來自盟國和中立國的人士組成，由怡和大班百德新少校（Major J. J. Paterson）指揮。成員有36名，其中有22名港燈僱員、8名自由法軍成員、及社會名流如賽馬會秘書及77歳的香港會所秘書德輔男爵。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18日下午，百德新少校與拉吉普營營長見面，均預計持續的砲火及濃煙有利日軍晚間登陸。曉士兵團隨後與D連失去聯絡，獲米杜息士營官兵增援。翌日，曉士兵團派遣支隊摧毀了位於砲臺山的日軍速砲小隊陣地，擊斃其指揮官的兩名少尉。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">早上7時30分，日軍砲兵隊砲擊太古及筲箕灣，同時空襲港督府及摩星嶺砲台。北角油庫被砲彈誤中起火，連同寶馬角的大火，濃煙隨東北風飄，形成煙幕，影響守軍視野。下午6時，筲箕灣橡膠廠及寶馬角油漆廠因砲擊起火，煙霧更濃。銅鑼灣英皇道因砲擊而滿佈車輛殘骸，北岸交通隨後完全癱瘓。 如今守備港島東北的印度拉吉普營多次被切斷通訊，大量探射燈失靈。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/17/173970/201712_Onthisday_11.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/17/173970/201712_Onthisday_11.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・十】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-17-hongkong-defense-war-1941--10.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・十】" /><published>2017-12-17T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-17T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-17-hongkong-defense-war-1941--10.html">&lt;p&gt;凌晨12時30分，日軍砲擊港島30分鐘，其間利用機動艇及民船活動，誘使英軍暴露陣地位置。早上7時30分，日軍終於不避攻擊市區，對維多利亞城實施近兩小時的「威嚇射擊」，砲擊住宅區、西環卑路乍砲台、甚至山頂及花園道一帶。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;砲擊過後，日軍再度派出軍使前往皇后碼頭勸降，英軍只以「不」回應。日軍代表頗感意外，並揚言接下來砲擊將不顧市區平民。英軍藉停火空檔，調動防禦部隊，重鋪受損電話線。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午11時，日軍第38師團指揮部召開會議，於12時30分發布進攻港島命令，決定在翌日潮漲時段登陸。下午，英軍發現日艦在港島南活動頻繁，維港對岸各處集結船隻及軍車，未能偵測日軍會於何時、從何處登陸。下午5時，英軍成功擊毀日軍多門火砲。砲戰持續入夜，令北角寶馬角起火，濃煙隨東風吹向維港，影響視界。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上，日軍左翼隊派出兩隊斥候渡海查探地勢。一隊被擊退，領隊陣亡；另一隊成功渡海，發現愛秩序灣西南側的沙灘沒有地雷，只有簡單鐵絲網及哨站，較原定登陸地段廣闊及免卻被交叉火力掃射的風險。18日清晨，斥候成功返回九龍，匯報英軍防線空隙，令左翼隊得以更改作戰計劃，更順利登陸。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;日軍進攻港島方案&quot;&gt;日軍進攻港島方案&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日軍將計劃作左右兩翼攻攻，在英軍防衛相對較弱，地段平緩、欠缺海堤的港島東北登陸。右翼部隊由第230聯隊及第228聯隊組成，分別由大環及牛頭角出發，登陸北角寶馬角，然後沿著大坑、渣甸山、太平山，向港島西的西高山推進。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;左翼部隊則由第229聯隊組成，由油塘灣及三家村出發，在愛秩序灣登陸後南行，經大潭水塘攻打紫羅蘭山，再轉往西高山。總括而言，兩翼部隊登陸後向南直奔黃泥涌，再橫掃至港島西，過程預計在一日內完成（類似一戰德軍施里芬計劃（Schlieffen Plan）的「旋轉門」設計）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">凌晨12時30分，日軍砲擊港島30分鐘，其間利用機動艇及民船活動，誘使英軍暴露陣地位置。早上7時30分，日軍終於不避攻擊市區，對維多利亞城實施近兩小時的「威嚇射擊」，砲擊住宅區、西環卑路乍砲台、甚至山頂及花園道一帶。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/16/173923/201712_Onthisday_10.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/16/173923/201712_Onthisday_10.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・九】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-16-hongkong-defense-war-1941--09.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・九】" /><published>2017-12-16T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-16T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--09</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-16-hongkong-defense-war-1941--09.html">&lt;p&gt;日軍繼續日夜猛轟港島，造成嚴重破壞。上午，日軍砲轟港島北的多個機槍堡，迫使守軍轉至替代陣地（alternative position）。下午2時30分，禮頓山遭受15至20分鐘猛烈砲轟，建築被毀，當地守軍轉移陣地。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;摩星嶺砲台連續第三日受到重砲轟擊。射擊指揮所通氣管被一枚24厘米砲彈擊中，貫穿了厚達15呎的泥土及外牆，幸而未有爆炸，未造成死傷。下午5時，摩星嶺砲台砲兵奉命暫時退後休整。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;西灣砲台、白沙灣砲台同樣遭受砲擊，高度測距儀及大量機槍堡受損。入夜後，日軍迫擊砲繼續攻擊，迫使16個機槍堡守軍轉至替代陣地，英軍無法修理及重新鋪設電話線，部份陣地因此通訊中斷。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;空襲方面，土生戰隊繼續出擊。下午1時，駐台灣第11航空艦隊（配備特設航空機運搬艦，而非空母）應要求出動44架次，空襲香港仔、筲箕灣、鯉魚門、摩星巔，共投下26枚800公斤、54枚250公斤及34枚60公斤炸彈。香港仔船塢嚴重受創，皇家海軍無法維修色雷斯人號驅逐艦，唯有將之擱淺。至此，皇家海軍乏力阻止日軍登陸。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;摩星嶺砲台簡介&quot;&gt;摩星嶺砲台簡介&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;由於香港心臟地帶位於港島西的維多利亞城，當年英軍興建了多座固定大砲砲台防衛。早在1845年，軍部已在現炮台里附近興建了香港最早一座砲台。1900年，軍部建議在摩星嶺興建砲台，鎮守香港西面海域。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1909年，工程開始。1912年，砲台裝備了5門9.2吋砲X型（BL 9.2 inch Mk X，砲管47倍徑，射程達26.7公里；9.2吋即234毫米），扼守維多利亞港西部及硫磺海峽等航運要道。軍部亦興建了西面射擊指揮總部及幾座掩蔽體。1930年代，其中2門大砲被移至赤柱砲台，以加強香港南面防衛。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">日軍繼續日夜猛轟港島，造成嚴重破壞。上午，日軍砲轟港島北的多個機槍堡，迫使守軍轉至替代陣地（alternative position）。下午2時30分，禮頓山遭受15至20分鐘猛烈砲轟，建築被毀，當地守軍轉移陣地。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/15/173883/201712_Onthisday_9.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/15/173883/201712_Onthisday_9.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・八】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-15-hongkong-defense-war-1941--08.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・八】" /><published>2017-12-15T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-15T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--08</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-15-hongkong-defense-war-1941--08.html">&lt;p&gt;上午起，日軍在間諜協助下砲擊港島北的機槍堡。日軍重砲繼續轟擊摩星嶺砲台，但未造成實際損傷。經歷轟炸機及重砲4小時轟炸，松林砲台受到嚴重破壞，砲兵被迫撤走，轉作步兵支援他部。當日，英軍主要反擊九龍水塘濾水廠附近、何文田以南、深水埗及美孚油庫的日軍陣地。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;空襲方面，陸軍土生戰隊發動了6次空襲、出動達80架次。海軍亦派出7架次，一同攻擊香港仔。一艘輔助巡邏艇重傷沉沒，船塢一片狼藉，但仍能勉強運作。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上7時25分，白沙灣砲台的探射燈發現有木筏及橡皮艇試圖接近港島。周邊地區英軍陣地隨即向魔鬼山一帶開火。魔鬼山上的日軍砲兵還擊，砲火持續半小時。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;松林砲台簡介&quot;&gt;松林砲台簡介&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1898年，英國軍備委員會建議在港島西北一座307米高的山頭興建砲台，增強防衛港島西面，防範法俄在遠東擴張（1902年英日締結同盟，1904年日俄爆發戰爭）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1901年，工程動工。1905年，砲台建成，配備2門6吋砲，為香港地處最高的砲台。1909年，來自英國本土的皇家砲兵總監，參觀松林砲台舉行的海岸攻擊演習。當日天氣欠佳，砲台朝5.5公里之外的海上靶子發11砲，7發命中，成續算是不錯。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1913年，由於軍部計劃於摩星嶺興建大型砲台，砲台兩門大砲被移除，處於空置狀態。1930年左右，砲台被軍部重新徵用，改裝成防空砲台，備有2門3吋高射砲，並加建了多座掩蔽體及營舍。松林砲台設施仍然甚為完整，是現時香港唯一以戰前型制遺留下來的防空砲台，現址現為龍虎山郊野公園一部分，軍營部分被改成為郊遊區。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">上午起，日軍在間諜協助下砲擊港島北的機槍堡。日軍重砲繼續轟擊摩星嶺砲台，但未造成實際損傷。經歷轟炸機及重砲4小時轟炸，松林砲台受到嚴重破壞，砲兵被迫撤走，轉作步兵支援他部。當日，英軍主要反擊九龍水塘濾水廠附近、何文田以南、深水埗及美孚油庫的日軍陣地。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/14/173839/201712_Onthisday_8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/14/173839/201712_Onthisday_8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・七】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-14-hongkong-defense-war-1941--07.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・七】" /><published>2017-12-14T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-14T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--07</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-14-hongkong-defense-war-1941--07.html">&lt;p&gt;是日，日軍各砲兵隊確立射擊陣地，240毫米榴彈砲安置於石梨貝水塘，150毫米加農砲定於大圍，150毫米榴彈砲及臼砲則散布九龍市區周邊。全體砲兵對港島實施有組織砲轟，發射了3,660發240毫米和150毫米砲砲彈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上午9時，卑路乍砲台（建於1886年，位於現西環寶翠園內）遇襲，觀測站及兩門4.7吋砲全毀，只剩一門6吋砲，印藉砲兵轉作步兵轉守他處。上午11時，白沙灣砲台（建於1903年，位於現杏花邨一帶）受密集砲轟，觀測站被毀。正午時分，摩星嶺砲台受襲，高射砲台彈藥庫中彈，一門高射砲被毀。砲擊更破壞通訊電纜，切斷英軍各地電話線路。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午，日軍空襲港島北砲台、香港仔的船隻、船塢發電站及油庫。同日，英軍於黃泥涌峽設立反砲擊指揮所（Counter Battery Headquarters），反擊在何文田及魔鬼山等地的日軍砲兵。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;日本陸軍第1砲兵隊簡介&quot;&gt;日本陸軍第1砲兵隊簡介&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第1砲兵隊，是1937年為了攻陷南京而編成的精銳砲兵部隊，其司令北島驥子雄被稱為日軍重砲兵一人。第1砲兵隊在香港戰役後，轉戰菲律賓的美軍要塞。第1砲兵隊攻佔香港時的陣容如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;第1砲兵司令部&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;重砲兵第1聯隊 （四五式240毫米榴彈砲×8門）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;獨立重砲兵第2大隊 （八九式150毫米加農砲×8門）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;獨立重砲兵第3大隊 （八九式150毫米加農砲×8門）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;野戰重砲兵第14聯隊第1大隊 （四年式150毫米榴彈砲×6門）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;獨立臼砲第2大隊 （鋼製150毫米臼砲×12門）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;砲兵情報第5聯隊 （測地中隊、標定中隊、音源中隊）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;第3牽引自動車隊&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">是日，日軍各砲兵隊確立射擊陣地，240毫米榴彈砲安置於石梨貝水塘，150毫米加農砲定於大圍，150毫米榴彈砲及臼砲則散布九龍市區周邊。全體砲兵對港島實施有組織砲轟，發射了3,660發240毫米和150毫米砲砲彈。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/13/173787/201712_Onthisday_7.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/13/173787/201712_Onthisday_7.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・六】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-13-hongkong-defense-war-1941--06.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・六】" /><published>2017-12-13T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-13T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--06</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-13-hongkong-defense-war-1941--06.html">&lt;p&gt;早上6時30分，色雷斯人號驅逐艦及四艘魚雷艇接走滯留三家村碼頭的英軍，但未能帶走運輸隊的騾仔。早上7時35分，日軍下令暫停軍事行動，派出由軍參謀率領的勸降軍使團乘小艇航向港島，並藉停火在九龍沿岸偵察英軍港島陣地及可行的登陸點。小艇還帶著在重光前夕就任署理總督之布政司詹遜秘書的夫人作人質。勸降書中提及：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;「香港命運已定，勝敗不言自明。…… 溯自開戰以來，貴軍雖努力作戰，但繼續抵抗必將斷送百萬無辜男女老幼之生命，此皆為貴國騎士道精神及我國武士道所不忍，望總督深思，立即承諾舉行獻城會議。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;出乎日軍意料之外，楊慕琦很快便回覆：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;「總督欣賞是次交流背後的精神，惟無論如何亦不能召開任何有關香港投降的會議或談判。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日軍勸降失敗後，於下午2時30分開始砲轟港島，擊中港島西摩星嶺砲台的3號9.2吋砲，使之報廢。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日軍既未動用「王牌」第1砲兵隊，亦較預期少花5日，就控制了九龍新界 。第38師團隨即選拔能夠游泳4公里的士兵組織「敢死隊」，由師團中兩名奧運游泳選手指導，希望乘勝追擊。但「敢死隊」遭英軍掃射造成死傷，計劃被迫終止。海上方面，即使第2遣支艦隊封鎖香港周邊水域，守軍砲艦及魚雷艇仍然活躍，登陸行動充滿風險。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日軍遂決定讓砲兵發揮十分威力，待準備周全才於18日晚上發動總攻擊，日期與原訂計劃一致。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">早上6時30分，色雷斯人號驅逐艦及四艘魚雷艇接走滯留三家村碼頭的英軍，但未能帶走運輸隊的騾仔。早上7時35分，日軍下令暫停軍事行動，派出由軍參謀率領的勸降軍使團乘小艇航向港島，並藉停火在九龍沿岸偵察英軍港島陣地及可行的登陸點。小艇還帶著在重光前夕就任署理總督之布政司詹遜秘書的夫人作人質。勸降書中提及：</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/12/173739/201712_Onthisday_6.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/12/173739/201712_Onthisday_6.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・五】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-12-hongkong-defense-war-1941--05.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・五】" /><published>2017-12-12T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-12T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--05</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-12-hongkong-defense-war-1941--05.html">&lt;p&gt;在砲兵掩護下，英軍按計劃撤兵，日軍只能與負責殿後的部隊交火。西九龍方面，上午7時，日軍混合挺進隊進入九龍市區，沿彌敦道南進，在尖沙咀天星碼頭與英軍印度旁遮普營（14th Punjab Regiment）及皇家蘇格蘭營駁火，但未能阻止後者登船撤退。當時支援日軍的黑幫人士乘機作亂，先被英軍印兵擊退，再被日軍挺進隊鎮壓。上午8時，日軍完全控制九龍市區及青衣島。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;東九龍方面，伊東武夫少將率領的日軍左翼於昨日晚上約10時未遭抵抗下登陸大水坑後，行進緩慢。伊東知悉英軍經已撤退後，即下令追擊，但受英軍埋在道路及其他易行地段的地雷阻礙。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;凌晨時份，日軍行至大老山附近。日出時份，第229聯隊第2及第3步兵大隊分別抵達飛鵝山及鑽石山。下午1時，第229聯隊於井欄樹集結。印兵則且退且戰，於九龍山脊行軍逾32公里，再到魔鬼山集結佈防，會合從九龍城登艦到山上設立總部的華里士及其參謀，可謂由舊班底殿後（華里士准將長期駐守印度，開戰前為拉吉普營營長）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下午2時30分，第229聯隊與英軍於馬游塘防線交火。其間 ，英軍發現最少一個日軍大隊嘗試沿小徑南下，立即下令五桂山砲兵觀測所指揮港島砲台砲擊阻止。下午5時，第229聯隊對防線中央發起攻勢，被拉吉普營擊退 。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上9時，由於補給無以為繼及希望拉吉普營替換港島防區重整後負責防守港島東北，但急需休整的皇家蘇格蘭營，莫德庇下令華里士率部撤出防線。英軍遂離開魔鬼山半島，前往三家村碼頭。撤退過程頗為混亂，有駁船因未依燈號而被友軍擊沉。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">在砲兵掩護下，英軍按計劃撤兵，日軍只能與負責殿後的部隊交火。西九龍方面，上午7時，日軍混合挺進隊進入九龍市區，沿彌敦道南進，在尖沙咀天星碼頭與英軍印度旁遮普營（14th Punjab Regiment）及皇家蘇格蘭營駁火，但未能阻止後者登船撤退。當時支援日軍的黑幫人士乘機作亂，先被英軍印兵擊退，再被日軍挺進隊鎮壓。上午8時，日軍完全控制九龍市區及青衣島。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/11/173696/201712_Onthisday_5.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/11/173696/201712_Onthisday_5.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・四】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-11-hongkong-defense-war-1941--04.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・四】" /><published>2017-12-11T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-11T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--04</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-11-hongkong-defense-war-1941--04.html">&lt;p&gt;凌晨12時正，日軍右翼第230聯隊第2大隊發動夜襲，撲向金山256及361高地，經歷葵涌高地地雷帶時有所傷亡，再與皇家蘇格蘭營正面衝突，以至白刃戰肉搏。激戰中聯隊第5中隊隊長被擊斃，蘇格蘭營B、C連連長雙雙陣亡。早上9時30分起，昂船洲、摩星嶺砲台等猛烈砲轟金山，阻礙日軍攻勢。眼見英軍左翼漸見單薄，大陸旅旅長華里士准將於早上11時下令山砲連及輜重部隊率先撤退。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;正午12時，駐港英軍司令莫德庇少將下令大陸旅撤出醉酒灣防線，退守港島。大陸旅於下午沿早已計劃的路線撤退，晚上陸續登艦離開九龍。下午3時，昂船洲守軍收到撤退命令開始撤離。下午4時30分，日軍登上無人駐守的金山山頂，控制附近一帶，酒井隆隨即下令佔領九龍市區。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上7時左右，日軍右翼沿青山道往九龍市區推進，但已錯失殲敵機會。晚上7時30分，華里士親率部往西抵達啟德，於9時30分到達油塘，在海灣防線建立指揮部安排撤退及殿後。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;醉酒灣防線gin-drinkers-line簡介&quot;&gt;醉酒灣防線（Gin Drinkers Line）簡介&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1920及1930年代，英國參謀長委員會屬下的聯合計劃小組討論香港防衛問題，建議在九龍山脈修築永久防線，阻止敵軍據之作為制高點控制維港，令港島北的船塢暴露於砲火下。而守軍需要獨自支撐約54日，直至艦隊抵港支援。此為醉酒灣防線於1934年興建的起源。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;醉酒灣防線工程以當時正在進行的城門水塘第三期工程作掩飾，最初叫Grasett內防線。防線起點為葵涌醉酒灣（已被填海，現為葵芳一帶），伸延至沙田、越過山嶺至西貢牛尾海，全長約18公里，防線扼守新界九龍間的要道，並確保市區食水供應。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;防線共有90個機槍堡、11個指揮所、3個炮兵觀測所，機槍堡間以交通壕連結。防線大致分為4個營級防禦區（defended localities），以互相支援的壕堡陣地、將敵人置於交叉火網下。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1938年，由於預計敵眾我寡及預計所限，參謀長委員會將防衛範圍縮窄為「保住港島」及「阻止日軍使用海港」，醉酒灣防線用途由最後據點改作拖延敵人（當時為機密），遂於4月終止未動工的工程。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">凌晨12時正，日軍右翼第230聯隊第2大隊發動夜襲，撲向金山256及361高地，經歷葵涌高地地雷帶時有所傷亡，再與皇家蘇格蘭營正面衝突，以至白刃戰肉搏。激戰中聯隊第5中隊隊長被擊斃，蘇格蘭營B、C連連長雙雙陣亡。早上9時30分起，昂船洲、摩星嶺砲台等猛烈砲轟金山，阻礙日軍攻勢。眼見英軍左翼漸見單薄，大陸旅旅長華里士准將於早上11時下令山砲連及輜重部隊率先撤退。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/10/173660/201712_Onthisday_4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/10/173660/201712_Onthisday_4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・三】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-10-hongkong-defense-war-1941--03.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・三】" /><published>2017-12-10T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--03</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-10-hongkong-defense-war-1941--03.html">&lt;p&gt;本日凌晨3時，英軍寡不敵眾，皇家蘇格蘭營A連長鍾斯上尉投降被俘，城門陣地失陷。這宗意外的捷報亦同時打亂日軍部署，師團長一度威脅砲擊第228聯隊，要求他們後退，而聯隊於日前在守軍砲火下奪取高地，隊長土井及眾隊員此時堅持「死守陣地」。雙方僵侍下，日軍並未立即進攻醉酒灣防線。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上6時，蘇格蘭營A連重組殘部，連同其餘三個連由醉酒灣防線前沿撤至金山。 活躍在青衣島的蟬號砲艦及昂船洲砲台則繼續砲擊，阻礙沿日軍沿青山道行軍。空軍亦有所行動，土生戰隊空襲英軍艦隻，特別是蟬號砲艦。下午，蟬號艦艏中彈，送往太古船塢維修。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日機同時散發勸降單張，駐港英軍總司令莫德庇少將指其「粗製濫造，對士兵毫無影響」，但當晚另一消息，卻滅絕守軍一切「增援或至」的奢望。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12月9日晚上，在馬來亞海域的皇家海軍遠東艦隊（代號Z Force）返航時，被日軍潛艇發現。12月10日正午時分，艦隊骨幹───旗艦威爾斯親王號戰艦和卻敵號戰鬥巡洋艦，在沒有任何空中掩護下遭86架日軍艦攻機及艦爆機圍攻，隨後被擊沉。艦上800多人陣亡，艦隊司令海軍上將菲利普殉艦，乃盟軍殉職軍官中最高軍階者。至此，盟軍在太平洋戰場只剩三艘主力艦。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;丘吉爾當時曾述：「在整個戰爭過程中，我從未收到比這個更直接的衝擊……當我在床上輾轉反側時，2艘軍艦全部沉沒的恐怖消息緊緊糾纏著我。」事件亦是史上首次純空中力量擊沉航行中的主力艦。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">本日凌晨3時，英軍寡不敵眾，皇家蘇格蘭營A連長鍾斯上尉投降被俘，城門陣地失陷。這宗意外的捷報亦同時打亂日軍部署，師團長一度威脅砲擊第228聯隊，要求他們後退，而聯隊於日前在守軍砲火下奪取高地，隊長土井及眾隊員此時堅持「死守陣地」。雙方僵侍下，日軍並未立即進攻醉酒灣防線。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/09/173592/201712_Onthisday_3v2-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/09/173592/201712_Onthisday_3v2-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・二】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-09-hongkong-defense-war-1941--02.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・二】" /><published>2017-12-09T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-09T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--02</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-09-hongkong-defense-war-1941--02.html">&lt;p&gt;日軍迫近醉酒灣防線時遇到更大阻力，右翼被昂船洲大砲轟擊，左翼亦於大圍受機槍砲火妨礙。按原訂方案，日軍會以4-5日部署步兵聯隊及砲兵隊，禁絕偵察以外的行動，再發動總攻擊，以期10日攻克九龍，3日佔領港島。可是，現場指揮官的判斷打亂了原訂計劃。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12月8日下午，土井定七大佐率領的第228聯隊抵達深圳，並在翌日早上向南急行軍 。土井登上針山、草山偵察，物色設立陣地的地點，發現城門河後方的255及341高地兵力薄弱，可作攻取金山防線的橋頭堡。當日下午，第228聯隊第3大隊（約500人）進入鉛礦坳，英軍開火阻擊。晚上8時左右，土井下令第3大隊奪取高地，突襲城門水塘以南的城門碉堡。由於下雨後大霧茫茫，負責防守的皇家蘇格蘭營A連第8排（連同連部共39人）的偵察兵及巡邏隊並未察覺日軍已漸漸靠近並渡過主壩拆除炸藥，摸黑進攻。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上11時10分，日軍攻佔位處最北的401A號機槍堡，兵分兩路攻向西邊的402號機槍堡及更高的砲兵觀測所。由於通訊兵離開連部所在的砲兵觀測所時未有按程序留下鎖匙，以致蘇格蘭營A連連長鐘斯上尉等人被反鎖站內。英軍寡不敵眾，於排部發動的反擊失敗，砲兵觀測所亦被圍攻。10日凌晨3時，鐘斯投降。此役中，土井部隊只有兩人陣亡、數人負傷、卻俘虜20多人。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;土井雖然成功在醉酒灣防線打開缺口，迫使英軍提早撤回九龍，但此舉擅自行動，並攻入第230聯隊轄區的城門口塘，違反軍令。土井的舉動在師團及軍司令部引起風波，軍長酒井隆一度揚言要軍法審判土井。結果，土井受到訓斥，第3大隊至對港島總攻時才被調回前線。此役戰功就被記入攻陷觀測所的第10中隊隊長若林東一中尉身上。「若林隊佔領」五字，至今仍可見於壁上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">日軍迫近醉酒灣防線時遇到更大阻力，右翼被昂船洲大砲轟擊，左翼亦於大圍受機槍砲火妨礙。按原訂方案，日軍會以4-5日部署步兵聯隊及砲兵隊，禁絕偵察以外的行動，再發動總攻擊，以期10日攻克九龍，3日佔領港島。可是，現場指揮官的判斷打亂了原訂計劃。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/08/173555/201712_Onthisday_2-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/08/173555/201712_Onthisday_2-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">【香港保衛戰當年今日・一】</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-08-hongkong-defense-war-1941--01.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="【香港保衛戰當年今日・一】" /><published>2017-12-08T12:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-08T12:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/hongkong-defense-war-1941--01</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/2017-12-08-hongkong-defense-war-1941--01.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;前言&quot;&gt;——前言——&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;第二次世界大戰中，法國戰役長45日，南京歷12日淪陷，長達18天的香港保衛戰中，守軍負隅頑抗，不比他國遜色。過千名本地及外藉軍人和平民為港捐軀，國藉包括英國、加拿大、印度、澳洲、紐西蘭、緬甸、荷蘭等等。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;今日，我們遠離戰爭的殘酷及苦難，但當年此地的英雄事蹟，默默提醒港人：和平及自由並非必然，仍係不同人士付出及犠牲，捍衛得來。不尊重歷史的政權，終會被歷史唾棄；但遺忘歷史的人民，同樣會被歷史遺忘。認識、正視及保護香港歷史，係市民不可推卸的責任。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;專頁前年整理的【香港保衛戰當年今日】系列，經修訂及重新製圖後重刊，希望有助普及這段歷史。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日軍空母機動部隊突襲珍珠港，藉癱瘓美軍艦隊而發動南方作戰， 侵攻東南亞各地，突破被ABCD包圍網經濟封鎖的局面。香港時間早上3時半，日軍第23軍司令部下達暗號「鷹」，下令香港作戰開始。兩小時後，駐港遠東三軍情報署偷聽到東京電台有關即將對英開戰的暗號，一小時內通知全體駐港英軍 。「大陸旅」佈置在邊境的兩隊「前進隊」隨即破壞跨越深圳河的橋樑，及青山道和大埔道的渡河點，阻礙日軍前進，退回九龍。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;香港時間早上6時50分，日軍出動空軍轟炸前深水埗軍營及啓德機場，炸毀英軍的4架空軍飛機及8架客機。主攻的土生戰隊主力轟炸民用機，表現差強人意，空襲功勞反而由負責護航的高月中隊低飛掃射所得。在此之後，日軍取得香港戰役的制空權。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;香港時間早上8時半，日軍經羅坊及羅湖越深圳河進攻香港。斥候隊及香港義勇防衛軍（HKVDC）裝甲車隊伏擊日軍，按原定計劃且戰且退，作遲滯防禦。英軍破壞工作幾乎徹底破壞新界現代交通網絡，直至1942年春季，鐵路隧道才重新開通，令日軍花上更多時間運送第1砲兵隊攻略要塞用的重砲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;晚上，部份滯港民國要人如宋慶齡、宋靄齡、孔令俊、孔令傑等人由國民政府專機接送由啟德機場離港。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--END--&gt;</content><author><name>Watershed Hong Kong</name></author><summary type="html">——前言—— 第二次世界大戰中，法國戰役長45日，南京歷12日淪陷，長達18天的香港保衛戰中，守軍負隅頑抗，不比他國遜色。過千名本地及外藉軍人和平民為港捐軀，國藉包括英國、加拿大、印度、澳洲、紐西蘭、緬甸、荷蘭等等。</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/07/173490/201712_Onthisday_1-960x960.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vjmedia.com.hk/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/07/173490/201712_Onthisday_1-960x960.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TEMPLATE</title><link href="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/0000-00-00-template.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TEMPLATE" /><published>-0001-12-31T22:56:15+06:55</published><updated>-0001-12-31T22:56:15+06:55</updated><id>https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/template</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://agorahub.github.io/pen0/hkers/0000-00-00-template.html">&lt;p&gt;PLEASE READ AND USE THIS TEMPLATE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EXCERPT ENDS (&amp;lt; 200 WORDS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;excerpt /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-template&quot;&gt;USE THE TEMPLATE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1- &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/agorahub/pen0/blob/master/_collections/_hkers/0000-00-00-template.md&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOWNLOAD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; AND RENAME: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2- EDIT IT AS YOUR OWN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commit-your-post&quot;&gt;COMMIT YOUR POST&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3- &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/agorahub/pen0/blob/master/_collections/_hkers/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COMMIT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; VIA UPLOAD.†&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;† MAY NEED A PULL REQUEST.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>AUTHOR</name></author><summary type="html">PLEASE READ AND USE THIS TEMPLATE. EXCERPT ENDS (&amp;lt; 200 WORDS).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/JFoSjco.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/JFoSjco.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>